Thanks dude.
Thanks dude.
Last stage.
Last stage.
Last clicks. mãe a
Last clicks. mãe a
e
e
d
d
m
m
e
e
Good night to many of my colleagues
許多本院的同仁 大家晚安
It is my pleasure to be here today to host our feast of knowledge today
我很高興今天在這裡主持我們今天的知識饗宴
Then you can see it from here
那大家可以從這邊看到
Today we are led by researcher Xu Yaru
我們今天是由徐雅如研究員
Tell us about the Modai earthquake and tsunami
為我們講以莫代大地震與海嘯
I think we may have to wait a while to explain this topic
我想這個題目我們可能要等一下解釋一下
Then let me introduce our keynote speaker today
那我先介紹一下我們今天的主講人
Dr Koh graduated from the Department of Earth Sciences, National Central University in 1997
許博士是在1997年畢業於國立中央大學地球科學系
is a very young and brilliant scientist
是非常年輕的傑出的一位科學家
After he finished his Ph.D.
他在唸完博士學位之後
Once worked as a postdoctoral researcher at the California Institute of Technology
曾經在美國加州理工學院擔任博士後研究
Returned to Academia Sinica 11 years ago in 2006
在2006年11年前回到中研院
From assistant researcher to assistant researcher
從助理研究員 助研究員 升到副研院
The researcher just became a political researcher two years ago
研究員兩年前剛剛身為政研究員
Wait a minute talks about his field of study
他的研究的領域等一下會談
Mainly use this global satellite island navigation system
主要是利用這個全球衛星島航系統
This is the GPS on everyone's phone
這是大家手機上的那個GPS
use this signal to observe the entire surface of the earth
用這種信號去觀測整個地表
deformation of the crust
地殼的變形
And our research on geodynamics
還有我們這種地體動力學這些研究
So the results of these studies
所以在這些研究的結果
can tell us something about earthquakes
可以告訴我們一些有關地震
About the tsunami caused by the earthquake
有關地震引起的海嘯
Mainly this is the last generation
主要是這個以末代
This term will be explained later
這等會會解釋一下這個專用名詞
Dr Xu's research
許博士的研究
We will invite him to serve as the main award today
我們今天會請他來擔任這個主獎人
yes he has had a lot of good results lately
是他最近有很多很好的結果
In 2010, he was awarded the Young Scholar Research Writing Award of the Academy
他曾經在2010年獲得本院年輕學者研究著作獎
This is a domestic research for young researchers
這是一個在國內對於年輕的研究者
Most of them are compared with the one who just started
多半都是比較剛剛開始他的那個
either teaching or research
或者是教書或者是研究方面
It is just starting to say that young scholars are more outstanding works awards
是剛剛就起步說年輕學者比較傑出的著作獎
In 2012, he won the Memorial Award of Mr. Wu Dayou from the Ministry of Science and Technology
那2012年獲得科技部吳大尤先生紀念獎
This is also a special award especially for young researchers
這也是特別給年輕的研究人員的一個特殊獎項
In 2017, this year won the Wu Jianxiong Academic Foundation
2017年今年獲得了吳建雄學術基金會的
Taiwan Outstanding Female Scientist Rookie Award
台灣傑出女科學家新秀獎
And this year there is also a Geological Society of the Republic of China
還有今年還有一個中華民國地質學會的
Wang Hanzhuo Dissertation Award
王漢卓論文獎
This is all in the geological world and the earth science world
這個是都是在這個地質界地球科學界
Most likely to be one of the late picks in the younger generation
最可能是在後期之秀在年輕的這一代中的一個教教者
So we are very happy to have Dr. Xu today
所以我們今天很高興請到了許博士
give us some introduction
給我們做一些介紹
He is at the Institute of Earth Sciences of the Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine
他是在中醫院地球科學研究所
So for this earth science research
所以對於這種地球科學的研究
And the thing about earthquakes that we are all most interested in
還有我們大家最感興趣的地震方面的東西
We all know that earthquakes are
我們大家知道地震是
It's something we can't avoid
實在是一件我們又無法避免
often come across
又常常會碰到
but for this
可是對於這個
If it happens, there will be great disaster or damage
如果一旦發生的話會有很大的災害或損害
So we hope to say that in this study
所以我們希望說在這個研究上面
be able to understand a little bit more about earthquakes
能夠對地震有多一點的了解
maybe one day
說不定有一天
We can be able to predict or at least
我們可以能夠預測或者至少
Some understanding of these can save them from harm
對這些有些了解能把這些傷害
able to minimize
能夠減到最少
So okay, I won't waste everyone's time anymore.
所以好 我就不再浪費大家的時間
Then please give warm applause
那請大家以熱烈的掌聲
Welcome to our today's keynote speaker, Dr. Xu Yaru
歡迎我們今天的主講人許雅如博士
Thanks
謝謝
First of all, I would like to thank Vice President Zhou for his introduction.
首先謝謝周副院長的介紹
And thank you very much
然後也非常感謝大家
It's "The Wind and Rain of the Hat" who came to listen to my speech
就是《帽子之風雨》前來聽我的這個演講
So today I'm going to target my past 10 years
那我今天會針對我過去10年來
Some research done in the screen generation to report to you
在螢幕代所做的一些研究跟大家報告
I will report the main words
主要的話我會報告一下
The cause of this screen generation earthquake
這個螢幕代大地震的成因
and a mechanism by which it occurs
以及它發生的一個機制
and some of the associated hazards that it caused this tsunami
以及它引發這個海嘯的一些相關的危害
Then how do we use some of the current observation methods
那我們如何用現今的一些觀測的手法
To understand the area where this large earthquake may occur
去了解這個大地震可能發生的區域
Then use some relevant references for follow-up disaster prevention and mitigation work
然後以後續一些防災減災工作的一些相關的參考
First of all, the first question I want to ask is
那首先呢第一個想要問的問題就是
Why We Are Studying the Great Earthquake of the Screen Generation
為什麼我們要研究螢幕代大地震
That's because the big earthquakes of the screen generation usually have a large scale
那因為螢幕代大地震通常它的規模都很大
And the range of its rupture is quite large.
而且它破裂的範圍也蠻大的
For example, in 2004, the scale of 9.2
譬如說在2004這個規模9.2的
This earthquake off the coast of Sumadawa
蘇門達瓦外海的這個地震
The earthquake itself has a different rupture length
這個地震它本身它破裂的長度有差
over a thousand kilometers
超過一千公里
And then he himself because of his mistake
然後呢他本身因為他的錯動
has grown above the seabed
已經發展到海床上面
So he created a big tsunami
所以說他產生了很大海嘯
This tsunami is in addition to
這個海嘯除了在
tree surface beat Yaqi Province
樹面打打雅其省
caused a lot of casualties
造成很大的一些傷亡
He spread thousands of miles away to Thailand
他傳播到千里之外的泰國
also caused many casualties
也造成很多的人員的一些傷亡
The earthquake killed a total of 250,000 people
那這個地震總共死了25萬人
So this is full
那所以說這個是滿
this damage
這個造成的這個傷害
It's actually quite impressive
其實是很可觀的
In other words, it is 2011
那另外的話就是2011年
This earthquake off the coast of Japan with a scale of 9.0
規模9.0的這個日本外海這個地震
What about the earthquake?
那這個地震呢
Although the Japanese government has expected that
雖然說呢日本政府已經預期說
there will be such an earthquake
會有這樣的地震
But I didn't expect the scale of this earthquake
但是沒有想到這個地震的規模
much higher than they estimated
遠遠高於他們所估計的
so you see
所以你看喔
In fact, in their coastal city
其實在他們的沿岸市上
There are already enough so-called tsunami walls
已經有足以所謂的海嘯牆
The height of this wall is about 7 meters to 8 meters
那這個牆的高度大概是7米到8米
But what about the unfortunate tsunami?
但是很不幸的這個海嘯呢
Far above this tsunami wall
遠遠高過這個海嘯牆
The slope height that can be defended
所能防禦的這個坡高
and then slow down here
然後就慢進了這
These many areas in Japan
日本的這些很多的區域
caused many casualties
造成很多的傷亡
In addition to the damage of the tsunami itself
除了這個海嘯本身的這些傷害之外
Also because of the earthquake
另外也因為這個地震
The nuclear disaster that caused this Fukushima
引發這個福島的核災
The Fukushima nuclear disaster actually caused some harm to the entire ecology
福島核災的話其實它對整個生態的一些傷害
just the longer one
就是更長遠的一個
long-term process
比較長遠的過程
There is a way to counteract such damage
才有辦法去擬平這樣的一些破壞
Japan because they are among the people for
日本因為他們在民眾對於
Earthquake disaster prevention work has been done thoroughly
地震防災的工作做得很徹底
So although its seismic scale
所以說雖然說它的地震規模
is also close to 9
也是將近是9
But its casualties were probably only 16,000
但是它死傷的人數大概只有16000人
With this number of people, about 250,000 people were killed or injured in the earthquake
跟這個數目的大家這個地震死傷的大概有25萬人
In fact, although it is an unfortunate large
其實它雖然是不幸中的大型
Earthquakes in addition to triggering these tsunamis
地震除了會引發這些海嘯
It's actually caused by strong vibrations on the surface
它事實上因為地表強烈的震動
it will cause some landslides
它會造成一些山崩土石流
This is the time of Wenchuan Earthquake
這個是溫川地震的時候
these landslides
這些山崩土石流
These villages under this mountain
在這個山貨下面這些村莊
also caused many casualties
也造成很多人員的傷亡
This is the 2016 Yumoto earthquake in Japan
這是2016年日本雄本地震
Some landslides near Aso volcano
在阿蘇火山附近的一些土石流
If the landslide flow is said to block the river course
土石流如果說它阻礙的河道
Yanse Lake
它就會產生燕色湖
If Yanse Lake breaks its embankment
燕色湖的話如果潰堤的話
In fact, it will also cause great harm to the downstream residents.
也事實上對下游居民也會造成很大的傷害
In addition to the strong vibrations of the earthquake itself
除此之外地震本身強烈的震動
It will also cause some older buildings
也會造成一些比較老舊的一些建築物
or the island tower of some poorly constructed building
或者是一些施工不良的建築物的島塔
For example, the island tower of the Weiguan Building in the 2016 Meinong Earthquake
譬如2016年美農地震維冠大樓的島塔
Although these are land earthquakes
雖然這些都是陸地震
But because of the big earthquake on the screen
但是因為螢幕帶的大地震
if it happened at the edge of the land
如果它是發生在陸地邊緣的話
all these possible disasters
這些所有可能的災害
Big earthquakes can happen on the screen
在螢幕帶大地震都可以發生
The next thing we learned about the big earthquake on the screen
接下來我們了解到螢幕帶大地震
possible harm
可能造成的危害
We just want to understand it and study it
我們就是要去了解它去研究它
Then today I will tell you
那今天我會跟大家
Let me introduce you to this process
以這樣的流程跟大家做一個介紹
what about first
那首先呢
I will first introduce the plate theory
我會先介紹一下板塊學說
Because it is closely related to the screen strip
因為它跟螢幕帶是息息相關的
Then we introduce
然後我們再介紹一下
One way the crust of the screen strip deforms
螢幕帶的地殼變形的一個方式
Then how do we use modern or
然後我們如何用現代的或者是
different methods of observation
不同的觀測手法
To understand the deformation of the screen with the crust
去瞭解這個螢幕帶地殼的變形的情形
Then what
然後呢
How to inversely calculate from this observation of Dibao
如何由地保的這個觀測去反算
The Situation of Chinese Americans at the Fault Level
在斷層面上的華裔情形
Then I will introduce
然後呢接著我會介紹
Two screen strips near Taiwan
台灣臨近的兩個螢幕帶
They are the Ryukyu screen belt and the Mara screen belt
分別是琉球螢幕帶跟馬拉螢幕帶
what next
那接著呢
Because most of the screen strips are in the sea
因為螢幕帶大部分都是在海裡
So we need to monitor other than on land
所以說我們除了在陸地上需要監測
In fact, we also need to monitor the deformation of the seabed
其實我們也需要監測海床的變形
So I'm going to introduce you to the deformation of the seabed
那所以我會為大家介紹一下海床的變形
Then we will have a little summary at the end
那最後我們會有一個小小的總結
what about first
那首先呢
Let us first introduce the plate theory
先來介紹一下板塊學說
Because the scientists actually warmed the
因為科學家們事實上在24季初溫
what did they find
他們發現呢
On this eastern coastline of South America
在南美洲的這個東部的海岸線
and
跟
fly some of the west coast
飛中的西部海岸一些
It seems that this protruding place and this concave place
似乎這個凸出來的地方跟這個凹進去的地方
These two can be pieced together if moved over
如果移過去這兩個是可以拼湊起來的
So what do you say?
那所以說呢
scientists are thinking
科學家們就在想說
Hey, are these two continents very close?
欸 這個兩個大陸是不是在很
Were they linked together in ancient times?
古遠的時候是不是連結在一起的
As for the doctors, they started looking for a lot of geological evidence
那醫師呢他們就開始去找很多的地質上的證據
to see the possibility
去看看這個可能性
Well, first of all, they will take a look at this ancient creature.
那首先呢他們就去看一下這個古生物
Discovered South America and Flying Facts
發現呢南美洲跟飛中的事實上
They have the same species that had the same creatures in ancient times
他們有相同的在遠古的時代有相同的生物的物種
What if at that time
那如果說在那個時候呢
South America and Fei Zhongge's One Atlantic
南美洲跟飛中閣的一個大西洋
There is no way this species can spread
這個物種是沒有辦法傳播的
So the first condition for their species to spread
所以呢他們物種可以傳播的首要條件
That is, these two continents are connected by Piling
就是這兩個大陸是皮靈在一起的
So they based on the distribution of these ancient organisms in different five continents
所以呢他們就根據這些古生物在不同的五大陸的分布
Then try to piece together what dimension these continents were in in the past
然後去拼湊出這些大陸在過去的位置是在什麼維度
What about the other words?
那另外的話呢
There is also some evidence of paleoclimate
還有一些古氣候的證據
For example, the direction in which a glacier is moving
譬如說冰川移動的方向
or from these three-pentagonal directions
或從這些三五角分布的方向
Then go to the previous time 300 million years ago
然後去把以前在三億年前的時候
In fact, the situation in the mainland is like this
其實大陸長的是這樣的一個情況
That is, the five continents are connected together in the world
就是這五大洲世上都連在一起
But now they are a separate
但是到現在他們卻是一個分開的
So scientists started to understand
所以科學家們就開始了解到
In fact, the plate itself is for drifting
其實板塊本身是為飄移
it is for exercise
它本身是為運動的
The new land may be in the central and deep city
那新的地可能會在中央及深城
Mainly because there are some radioactive elements in the ground and below
主要是因為地底和下面有一些放射性元素
can provide some fun
可以提供一些樂園
So the new land may be in the central and deep city
所以新的地可能會在中央及深城
Then move slowly to the sides
然後往兩旁慢慢的移動
that's why
那因為呢
Just move to the side
就是往兩旁移動的話
The sun is cooling down at once
這個太陽立刻就慢慢冷卻
It increases in density after cooling
冷卻之後它密度增加
After the density increases, it will slowly sink
密度增加之後它就會慢慢的下沉
And then finally the screen is under the continental plate
然後最後就螢幕在大陸板塊的下面
Well, this actually has the above when we boil water
那這個其實有以上在我們煮開水的時候
If there is a paradise below
如果說下面有個樂園
Then the water will move to both sides
那這個都水就會往兩旁運動
which is similar to
這是類似的
In the process of cloaking the oceanic crust
在海洋地殼隐默的過程當中
friction with the upper plate
會跟上部的板塊產生摩擦作用
And then there's what's called an earthquake
然後就會發生所謂的地震
That's why there are many big earthquakes in the Era
這就是為什麼在隱默代會有很多一些大的地震
that's why it happened
就是因為這樣發生的
If we look at the past over 4000 years
如果我們去看一下過去在4000多年
Distribution of Earthquakes in World History
這個世界歷史的地震的分布
You can see that red represents the number of casualties
大家可以看到紅色是代表傷亡的數
More than 1000 people
超過1000人的
Yellow is probably the number of casualties between 100 and 1000
黃色大概是傷亡的數是介於100到1000人的
Other colors are relatively minor earthquakes
其他顏色就是比較有些次要的地震
You can see that the major earthquakes are around plate boundaries
你可以發現主要的地震都是環繞在板塊的邊界
For example, along the perimeter of the Pacific plate
譬如說在沿著太平洋板塊的周遭
Then the South Park of Eurasia
然後歐亞大陸的南園
Near the Sanda Trench we just talked about
我們剛剛講的這個桑達海溝這邊附近
In fact, there are quite a few earthquakes here.
其實這邊的話其實也有蠻多地震
But because there are relatively few people living here
但是因為這邊居住的人事上是比較少
So the casualties are not as heavy as in other places
所以傷亡就沒有像其他地方這麼的慘重
This is also the distribution of historical tsunamis
這也是歷史的海嘯的分布
Probably also the distribution of historical tsunamis over the past 3600 years
大概也是過去3600年來歷史海嘯的分布
There are many causes of tsunamis
海嘯的成因其實有很多種
it can be triggered by an earthquake
它可以由地震引發
Can be erupted by underwater volcanoes
可以由海底的火山噴發
or caused by landslides under the sea
或者是由海底的山崩所造成
If it is caused by an earthquake
如果是地震引發的話
It is displayed here in a circle
是用圈圈的方式在這邊展示
you can see that is to say
你可以看到就是說
Most of these catastrophic tsunamis
大部分這些災害性的海嘯
In fact, they all revolve around the Pacific plate.
事實上也都是圍著太平洋板塊
nearby
附近
Circum-Pacific Seismic Belt
就是環太平洋地震帶
it's happening here
這邊在發生
After we learn about some of the behavior of screen strips
我們了解到螢幕帶的一些行為之後
Let's see if it's on screen
我們再看它到底是在螢幕帶的時候
How did the crust of this place deform?
這個地方的地殼是怎麼去變形的
here is a
這邊是一個
sorry
對不起
ok , sorry , let ' s broadcast like this
好,不好意思,我们这样播好了
This picture depicts the deformation behavior of hidden tendrils
这张图描写就是隐蔓带变形的行为
You can see that the oceanic crust is slowly creeping down
大家可以看到这个是海洋地壳慢慢地在隐蔓下去
But because it is a fault because of the relationship between the underlying layer
但是因为它断层因为潜层的关系
moshaleh effect it belongs to the state of doing
摩沙列作用它是属于所做的状态
Then it can continue to move in a deeper place
然后在比较深的地方它可以持续的运动
The cryptic effect is going on all the time
隐蔓作用就是一直地进行下去
So in places closer to the trench
所以在比较靠近海沟的地方
this is the place
也就是这个地方
The entire continental crust will be arched
这整个大陆地壳会被拱起来
You can see there is a reference station GPR station here
你可以看到这边有一个参考站GPR站
inland direction movement
內陸方向移動
until this station reaches the maximum displacement
直到這個站到達最大的位移
Energy accumulation has no way to accumulate more energy
能量累積已經沒辦法再累積更多能量
it produces earthquakes
它就產生地震
If the earthquake breaks out to sea it creates a tsunami
如果地震破裂到海上就產生了一個海嘯
and caused a lot of casualties
然後造成了很多大的傷亡
after the whole gag is over
在整個塞口結束之後
Energy starts to accumulate again
能量又開始會重新累積
Then start the cycle of the next earthquake
然後開始下次地震的周期循環
This is the lattice deformation of the screen strips we often see
這是我們常常看到的螢幕帶的立格變形
So in a place close to the sea structure
所以說在靠近海構的地方
It will be found that after the earthquake
就會發現在地震發生後
Has some terrestrial imaging role
有一些陸地成像的作用
For example, this is a coconut tree by the sea
譬如說這個是海邊的椰子樹
Basically, these coconut trees should grow above the intermediary zone
基本上這些椰子樹應該是要生長在朝間帶以上
But now they are all within the range of the interzone
但是現在他們都已經在朝間帶的範圍
and many coconut trees are dead
而且很多椰子樹都死了
Mainly because of the coast caused by this earthquake
主要就是因為這個地震造成的海岸
generate a large number of renders
產生大量的呈現
caused the death of these many coconut trees
造成這些很多椰子樹的死亡
Here is also a case presented in the ground
這邊也是一些入地呈現的一個case
If we were to take a closer look
如果我們要仔細的去看一下
Screen deformation behavior with earthquakes
螢幕帶地震的變形行為
We can simplify slightly
我們可以稍微簡化
represented by the following diagrams
用下面這些圖來表示
Suppose this line represents the surface
假設這條線代表是地表
This line is the interface of the panel of the screen
這條線是螢幕的板塊的界面
We can move faults across plate interfaces
我們可以把斷層在板塊界面上運動
represented by this diagram
用這個簡圖來表示
We can see this line
我們可以看到這條線
The above is called the top plate, and the bottom is called the bottom plate
以上叫上盤,以下叫下盤
If this place can be
如果說這個地方可以進行
free screen words
自由的螢幕的話
location across the fault
跨過斷層的位置
a surface deformation you see
你看到的一個地表變形
It's just a jiedihan tree
就是一個潔堤函樹
That is to say, everything east of this line belongs to ascending
也就是這條線以東都是屬於上升
All west of this line are offline
這條線以西都是下線
It's because of fault sneaking
是因為斷層潛步
it belongs to a locked state
它是屬於一個鎖住的狀態
So we often observe
所以說我們常常觀測到
The phenomenon is that the deformation is very small near the fault
現象就是在靠近斷層的地方變形量很小
But far from the fault
但是在遠離斷層的地方
The magnitude of its movement is just like that of the original factory.
它的運動的量級就跟在原廠的
That is, the plates move at the same speed.
就是板塊的運動速度是一樣的
That's because earthquake observations can tell us
那因為地震的觀測可以告訴我們
where the fault might be located
斷層的位置可能在什麼地方
So what?
所以說呢
we have this
我們有了這個
The observation data of this original factory
這個原廠的這些觀測的資料
There are also some observational data based on faults
還有一些靠斷層的觀測的資料
we can speculate
我們就可以去推測
What should the Jianghai Earthquake look like?
江海地震應該會長什麼樣子
Because what these two villages need is equal to this
因為這兩個鄉家要需要的是等於這個
this cold tree
這個寒樹
Then we can speculate
那我們就可以去推測呢
What about the Jianghai earthquake?
這個江海這個地震呢
the extent to which it may break when it occurs
發生時它可能破裂的範圍
Then its possible fault geometry
然後它可能的斷層的幾何形態
what is it like
是什麼樣的樣子
what if
那如果呢
Let's look at it another way
我們換一個方式來看看就是
This is the deformation behavior of the surface
這個是地表的變形的行為
Then if we look at the motion behavior on the fault
那如果我們看斷層上的運動行為
can be represented by this diagram
就可以用這個圖表示
This representative is Fault Huayi
這個代表是斷層華宜
The case of a distribution at different depths
在不同深度的一個分布的情形
You can imagine the energy slowly accumulating at a relatively deep place before an earthquake occurs
你可以想像在地震發生之前能量在比較深處的地方慢慢累積
Because in a relatively deep place, because of the relationship between the delayed temperature and pressure characteristics
因為在比較深處的地方,因為延遲溫壓特性的關係
it's some plastic deformation
它是進行一些塑形的變形
So the plate can always be on the screen
所以板塊可以一直的螢幕
Then the energy slowly accumulates in the deep place
然後能量慢慢在深的地方去累積
If we assume that the line of earthquakes in this place is around 1000 years
如果我們假設這個地方地震的在線周圍是1000年
Then this fault slips at a rate of 2mm per year
然後這個斷層滑移的速率是每年2mm
Then you know that after 1000 years of sliding
那你就知道說它滑了1000年之後
It has actually accumulated 20 meters of this energy
它事實上就已經累積了20米的這樣的能量
Then the process of accumulating energy is a very slow process
那這個在累積能量過程它是一個很緩慢的過程
However, when an earthquake occurs, it is a very fast process.
可是在地震發生的時候卻是一個很快的過程
Let's say it's been 1000 years
譬如說這個已經過1000年
Then the upper fault has reached a zero connection
然後上面這個斷層它已經到一個零接子
an earthquake rupture
就產生一個地震破裂
This earthquake rupture may take 20 to 30 seconds
這個地震破裂可能就是20秒到30秒事情
Then the whole rupture is done
然後這整個破裂就已經完成
so you can imagine
所以你可以想像喔
You have to accumulate energy for 1000 years and that's it
你要把累積1000年的能量就是這樣
Released at 20 seconds and 30 seconds
在20秒跟30秒釋放出來
the harm it caused
它造成的這個危害
Of course it is considerable
當然是很可觀的
At this time, if its energy is fully released
這時候如果它能量完全釋放出來
Then it will slide 20 meters
那它就是會滑動20米
Then if you slide 20 meters
那如果滑動20米的話
this is if your family
這是如果你的家庭
If I'm next to the fault line
我再斷層線旁邊的話
I think it should be asexual
我想應該是無一性
will be greatly damaged by these
都會受到很大的這些破壞
if it doesn't fully suspect
那如果它沒有完全懷疑
For example, in some places it is just
譬如說有些地方它只是
it doesn't release all the energy
它沒有把所有能量釋放出來
after the earthquake
那在地震發生過後
It will also have a persistent so-called post-earthquake doubt
它還會有持續的所謂的震後懷疑
to release the energy
去把這些能量釋放出來
Then this time scale may be
那這個時間尺度可能就是
Timescales of years to decades
幾年到數十年的時間尺度
Then this is probably one
那這樣這個大概就是一個
One way the Earth's crust deforms
地殼變形的一個方式
Then let's see
那接下來我們就來看一下
Sumatra Screen Strip
蘇門達拉螢幕帶
Since this place was in 2004
因為這個地方在2004年
This magnitude 9.2 earthquake occurred
發生了這個規模9.2的地震
Then this green area
那這個綠色的這個區域
is the range where it breaks
就是它破裂的範圍
Then one degree is roughly equal to 110 kilometers
然後一個一度大概是等於110公里
you see how far it breaks
你看它破裂的範圍
In fact it has been more than 10 degrees
實際上已經有超過10度
So there's more than 1,000 kilometers of rupture
所以是有1000多公里的破裂
What about this hidden belt?
那这个隐摸带呢
In fact, it is the junction of the hard Austrian plate and the Shangda block
事实上它是硬奥板块跟上达地块的交接处
The aggregate number of that plate is about 57 mimi per year
那板块的聚合数位大概是每年有57个米米左右
Except for the magnitude 9.2 earthquake in 2004
那除了2004规模9.2地震
It actually had another earthquake with a magnitude of 8.7 after 2005
它事实上在2005后面又发生了一个规模8.7的地震
Then follow up
然后后续呢
Earthquakes of magnitudes 7 and 8 also occurred in Sumida West Toilet
在苏美达西厕也发生了规模7跟8的地震
Then you can see there are some
那大家可以看到这边还有一些
For example, the magnitude 7.9 earthquake in 1881
比如说1881年的地震规模7.9
1797 and 1833
1797跟1833
those old earthquakes
那这些老的地震
how scientists know to say
科学家们是如何知道说
There was a self-written earthquake in that era
在那个时代曾经发生过自写地震呢
OK, let's make an introduction for you next.
好 那我们接下来为大家做一个介绍
It is how we monitor the deformation process of these vertical shells
就是我们如何去监测这些立殼变形的过程
then we used various methods
那我们使用了各种不同的方法
A way to compare current observations is to
比较现今的观测的方法就是
Global Navigation WeChat Positioning System
全球导航微信定位系统
Interferometry with Synthetic Aperture Radar
跟合成孔镜雷达干涉测量
This is all using WeChat technology
这个都是利用微信的技术
Then what
然后呢
If you want to know the relatively old events
如果想要知道比較無老的事件的話
you have to rely on some examples
就必須要靠一些例子的方法
For example, let's go pick some sea-grass
譬如說我們去採一些海接的
some nutrition for dating
一些營養去做定年
or we go to see the coral reef
或者是我們去看珊瑚礁
an example of his growth
他的生長的一個例子
Then I'll introduce you one by one
那隨後我會為大家一一做介紹
First of all, let's introduce
那首先我們先來介紹
GNSS
全球導航衛星定位系統
What about this? In fact, he is a
那這個呢其實呢他是一個
It is the same as our usual car navigation
跟我們常用的這個汽車導航是一樣的
It's just that the accuracy of car navigation is actually
只是說汽車導航的精度事實上
maybe a few meters
可能是到幾米
But we do this scientific research
但是我們做這個科學研究
The precision of our medicine may be up to
我們藥的精度可能是到
The level of minimeter
minimeter這個等級
In fact, now this
那事實上呢現在這個
There are different countries in the sky
天空上有各國不同
different countries have satellites
不同國家都有衛星
Then do the positioning
然後去做定位這件事情
Like the United States, there is this GPS system
像美國就有這個GPS的系統
In Russia, there is a Gonus system
那俄國的話有Gonus系統
Then in Japan they have the QVSS system
然後日本他們有QVSS系統
Then EU has this potential rate system
那EU有這個潛力率系統
Then mainland China also has their Beidou system
然後中國大陸也有他們的Beidou系統
What about these satellites?
那這些呢衛星呢
is probably
就是大概是
The satellite orbits at an altitude of about 20,000 kilometers
衛星的軌道大概是在2萬公里的高空
Then its track design is different
然後它軌道設計都各有不同
But its main essence is to wish to say
但是它主要的精髓就是希望說
We are anytime anywhere
我們在任何時間 任何地點
Can receive at least three or more satellites for positioning
都至少可以收到三顆以上的衛星來進行定位
So why do you need three satellites?
那為什麼需要三顆衛星呢
Then we can use this diagram to illustrate
那我們可以用這個圖外說明
What if I'm the captain
假設呢 我是這個船長
I don't know where I am now
那我現在不知道我身材何處
Then I went to receive the signal from this satellite
然後我就去接受這個衛星的訊號
Then receive the time from the satellite signal
然後從衛星訊號接受這個時間
I know how far I am from this satellite
我就知道我離這個衛星有距離多遠
Let's say I'm a thousand kilometers away from this satellite
假設我離這個衛星一千公里好
then i know
那我就知道說
All my positions on this ship
所有我的這個船的位置
May be anywhere on this garden boat
可能會在這個園舟上任何一個位置
But it doesn't tell me where I am
但是它並不能告訴我我在哪一個位置
So I have to go and receive the second satellite
所以我就必須要再去接受第二顆衛星
Then hand over the other garden
然後就交出另外這個園
so i know
那所以我就知道說
my location is not in this location
我的位置不是在這個位置
right here
就是在這個位置
but i want to make sure
但是我要確定
Is it this location or this location
到底是這個位置還是這個位置
I have to accept the second satellite
我就必須要接受第二顆衛星
The third WeChat signal
第三顆微信的訊號
then i know
然後我才知道
So I'm right here
原來我現在就是在這個位置
That's why we need
這就是為什麼我們需要
Three WeChat to do this navigation
三顆微信來做這個導航
to do positioning
來做定位
what about the fact
那事實上呢
We have also done a lot in Taiwan
我們在台灣也部了很多
The so-called fixed station of this GPS
所謂的這個GPS的固定站
Then we mainly accept
那我們主要是接受
This signal from the US WeChat
這個美國的微信的這個訊號
what about these
那這些呢
Where are these side stations?
這些側站呢
is that we're going on a regular basis
就是我們要去定期的
to measure its coordinates
去量測它的坐標
Then there is this coordinate change
然後有這個坐標的變化
we'll know
我們就可以知道
One state for each side station movement
這每一個側站運動的一個狀態
What about this picture?
那像這張圖呢
Different colors represent different units
不同的顏色代表是不同的單位
point of color
布色的點
The red color is from the Meteorological Bureau and the Earth Institute.
那紅色是氣象局跟地球所
colored dots
所布色的點
then blue is the interior
然後藍色是內政部
point of color
布色的點
Then green is other units
然後綠色就是其他單位
a point of the color
所布色的一個點
That's what we do wild
那這是我們做野外
Some circumstances of residence
住業的一些情形
Some of these points are called fixed stations
這些點位有的叫做固定站
fixed station means
固定站就是說
It is recording data 24 hours a day
它是24小時在記錄資料
Instruments and antennas are left in this place
儀器跟天線都是留在這個地方
then we will be on the surface
那我們會在地表
we'll fight underground
我們會在地底下打
then there is a stone
然後有個石質
Then when we make a vegetable gallery, it is a finalized product
然後我們做菜廊的時候就是定型定品
and then go and measure this rocky center point
然後去測量這個石質中心點
This coordinate changes over time
這個坐標隨時間的變化
Then this one is like a mobile plant in the wild.
然後這個呢就是像野外移動栽
is that it is not fixed
就是它並不是固定栽
We may measure once a year
我們可能是一年去測量一次
Then observe the change of this coordinate with time
然後去觀測這個坐標隨時間的變化
Then, in fact, this field work is quite hard.
然後呢其實說這個野外工作還滿辛苦
Then also full of horror
然後也滿驚悚的
I remember almost twenty years ago
我記得大概快二十年前
Sometimes I go to Chiayi with my classmates
有的時候我跟我同學到嘉義
Mei Shan Lane to do this field work
梅山巷去做這個野外工作
Then it was about three or four o'clock
然後那時候就是大概三四點
afternoon time
下午時間
then it was almost afternoon
然後已經快下午後
thunderstorm rainy day very dark
雷震雨天很黑
That's because our field survey goes once a year
那因為我們這個野外的測量一年去一次
So the grass basically grows taller than a person
所以那個草基本上長得比人還要高
Then we all have to take the knife
然後我們都要拿著材刀
Then rummage in the grass to find our spots
然後在草中裡面翻來翻去找我們的點
Because this point is actually not very easy to find
因為這個點其實並不是很好找
sometimes covered with soil
有時候還會被土覆蓋
As a result, we couldn't find it after searching for a long time.
結果呢我們就找半天都找不到
Then I separated from my classmates
然後呢我跟我同學分開
separately to find
分別去尋找
It didn't take long
結果沒過多久
There's a grave with a picture on it
竟然有一個墳墓上面有張照片
right at me
就正對著我
Then
然後
at that time
那時候
I feel a current
我就感覺到有股電流
all the way down my spine
從我的脊椎下面一直
wear to forehead
穿到腦門
Then for the first time I experienced what it means to have a chill down your spine
然後我第一次體會到什麼叫背脊發涼
because then i knew
因為那個時候我就知道
wow, it really is
哇 原來真的是
It really feels like there is electricity
真的是有電流的感覺
At that time, the previous life thought
那時候前一世是想
I really need to get out of this place
我真的要趕快離開這個地方
Yes, okay follow up
對 還好後續
When I told this joke to my assistant the day before yesterday
我前天講這個笑話給我的助理聽的時候
he asked me
他問我說
do you remember what that photo looked like
你還記得那個相片長什麼樣子嗎
I'll just talk to him
我就跟他講說
i just don't remember
我就好不要記得
yes it's actually
對 這其實
We actually have a lot of these in the wild
我們出野外其實有滿多這種
some assortment
各式各樣的一些
Some are actually quite scary
有一些其實是滿驚悚的
but
但是
Even we outdoor public still have to be very careful
就是我們野外公眾還是得是要很小心
Because in fact, there are often various states
因為其實常常會有各種不同的狀態
Will appear
會出現
Okay then I'll stop talking about horror
好 那我就不要再講驚悚的
Let's move on
我們接下來繼續講
Then this is our Taiwan GPS fixed
那這個就是我們台灣GPS固定
in our measured
在我們所量測到的
The movement speed of the test battle is long
測戰的運動速度長
That's a GPS watch
那這是GPS的作表
need time series
需要時間序列
This is the east-west component, the north-south component and the vertical component
這是東西分量南北分量跟垂直分量
So if we
所以我們如果
For example, this is the record from 2004 to 2017
譬如說這是從2004年到2017年的紀錄
Then if we are doing measurements every day
那如果我們就是每天都有去做測量的話
This is the fixed station data
這是固定站資料
we can get a point
我們就可以得到一個點
Then there are long-term observations
然後有長期的觀測
We can get this time series of a motion
我們就可以得到一個運動的這個時間序列
Then we can do linear regression
然後我們可以去做線性回歸
We know the speed of Ce Zhan's movement
我們就知道策戰的運動速度
Then when the earthquake happened
然後在地震發生的時候
For example, this is the Meifeng earthquake
譬如說這是美鳳地震
This is a battle near Guan Temple
這是在觀廟附近的一個策戰
then you can find out
那你就可以發現
when the earthquake happened
地震發生的時候
it will result in the displacement
它就會產生統政位移
So there will be a jump here
所以這邊會有一個jump這樣子
there will be a discontinuity
會有一個不連續
Then there will be some post-earthquake displacement
然後還會有一些震後的位移
Then slowly it will return to
然後慢慢的它會回復到
It is the relatively linear one before the earthquake.
就是震前的這個比較線性的
a state of motion
一個運動的一個狀態
then we can use this information
那我們就可以利用這些資料
to do a lot later
來做後面很多
It is some follow-up research work
就是後續的一些研究工作
Well, besides these, this global navigation satellite positioning system
那除了這些這個全球導航衛星定位系統
We can also use this
我們也可以利用這個
Core Aperture Mirror Radar Gamma Layer
核心孔鏡雷達甘色層
sound appreciation
叫做音賞
The English name is here
這個英文名是在這裡
Basically it is also a data using satellite
基本上它也是利用衛星的一個資料
So this is where the satellites fly
所以這邊是衛星飛行的軌道
Then it has a
然後它有一個
This one can sweep the floor
可以去掃地表的這個
It uses the radar slope to sweep a feature on the surface
它用雷達坡去掃地表的一個地物
And because of the scan time difference?
然後因為這個掃的時間差呢
I know this direction
我就知道這個方向
From satellite to any point on the surface
從衛星到地表上的任何一點
Then I can know the distance in this direction
然後我就可以知道這個方向的距離
The amount of change
的改變量
Let's say there's a volcano here
假設說這邊有個火山好了
What about when you sweep the terrain?
你地勢掃的時候呢
Its shape is like this
它的形狀是這樣
but behind
但是後面呢
Because the volcano has produced some deformation
因為火山有產生一些變形
What about during the second sweep?
在掃射第二次的時候呢
It has a difference amount to the bit
它向位就有一個差異量
Then you can have this bitwise difference amount
那你就可以有這個向位的差異量
To calculate is along the
去計算就是沿著
How big is the deformation depending on the direction of the satellite?
視衛星方向的這個變形量是有多大
Then this is what we use
那這個呢就是我們利用
synthetic aperture
合成孔徑
Radar interferometry data
雷達乾涉測量資料
Go Sweep Out During Beauty Earthquake
去掃出來在美容地震的時候
These deformed strips around
在附近的這些變形的條帶
These are the changes in phase
這些是相位的變化量
We can take it and go through some calculations
我們可以把它再去經過一些計算
Convert it to the potential of the ground resonance on the east and west
把它轉換成東西上的地表同振的位量
vertical position
跟垂直的位量
then you can see that
那你就可以看到就是說
In the words of beauty earthquake
在美容地震的話
In the market near Guanmiao
在官廟附近市上
TSMC has more than 10 cm on the market
台積量市上有超過有10公分
It's actually pretty big
其實是蠻大的
There is some deformation of about 5 to 10 cm in the horizontal volume
水平量有5到10公分左右的一些變形
What I just talked about are some more realistic observation methods.
那剛剛講的是一些比較現實的觀測方法
So if we want to know about some older earthquakes
那如果我們想要知道一些年代比較久遠的地震
we have to rely on the sea
我們就必須要靠海接
For example, Haijie
比如說海接的話
There are many seashores like these in eastern Taiwan
像台灣東部有很多海邊的這些結底
For example, the stone ladder is leveled.
那譬如說在石梯平好了
This is some research done by a Japanese research team in Taiwan
這是一個日本的研究團隊在台灣做的一些研究
Then this is Haijie near Shitiping
那這個是石梯平附近的海接
Then it goes from the lowest level to the highest level
那它從最低的這一階到最高的這一階
About 20 meters away
大概差了有20米
then it has several stages
那它有好幾個階段
The geologists are going to collect some rocks on this base
那地質學家們就在這個基地上面去採一些岩漾
then do research
然後去做研究
They know the history of these grounding platforms
他們就知道這些接地台深的歷史
Some of the history of these platform depths are related to the rise and fall of the sea level
這些台深的歷史有些是跟海水面的上升下降有關
Some are related to the depth of the earth
有些是跟地深有關
They have to do some progressive analysis
他們就必須要去做一些進步的分析
like this beautiful grounding
像是這種很漂亮的接地
Can do some related follow-up research work
可以去做一些相關的後續的研究的工作
In addition to coastal grounding, you can also use the belt area
除了海岸接地還可以利用樂帶地區的話
coral reef
就可以利用珊瑚礁
Coral reefs are actually coral reefs because it only grows below sea level
珊瑚礁事實上珊瑚礁因為它只能在海平面以下生長
So we can take advantage of this condition
所以我們可以利用這個條件
Go see how we use coral reefs to record the history of earthquakes
去看看我們如何用珊瑚礁來記錄地震的歷史
This records the growth process of a coral reef
這個就記錄一個珊瑚礁生長的過程
this is how high it grows and this is the time
這是它生長的高度這是時間
Then the coral reef slowly grows taller
然後珊瑚礁慢慢的長高
so you can see it growing higher and higher
所以你可以發現它生長的高度越來越高
getting higher over time
隨著時間越來越高
at this time if there is
這個時候如果有
It can't grow taller after it touches the sea level
它碰到海平面之後它就沒辦法長得更高
it can only grow sideways
它只能往旁邊生長
So its height is to maintain the video
所以它高度就是維持視頻
But what if there is an event that causes the sea floor to collapse?
但是呢 如果有一個事件造成海床台身的話呢
Basically, the growth height of these coral gums behind it will be shorter than the original ones.
那基本上呢 它後面這些珊瑚膠生長的高度就會比原來來的矮
And what if there's a seismic event that causes the sea floor to appear?
那如果呢 有一個地震事件造成海床呈現
The height of the coral glue that grows behind it can be higher than the one that came before
它後面長的這個珊瑚膠高度 又可以比之前來的來的高
OK so we can go to these screens nearby
OK 所以呢 我們就可以去這些螢幕在附近
Find these large coral gels
找這些大型的珊瑚膠
Then we cut it open, and after cutting it open
然後呢 我們把它剖開 然後剖開之後呢
You take some of these samples for dating
你取這些 這些一些炎樣去進行定年
Then go and see, that is, when
然後呢 再去看看就是說 在什麼時候
It has some, for example, massive die-off of coral gum
它有一些 譬如說珊瑚膠大量的死亡
Then it may be related to some earthquake events
那它可能就是跟一些地震事件是有關的
Then use this to find some older earthquake events
然後藉此呢 去找尋一些比較古老的一些地震的事件
Well, if the earthquake is big enough, we can actually directly
那如果地震夠大的話 其實我們可以直接
Measure the amount of coral gel and we'll know
量測這個珊瑚膠的位量 我們就知道說
How much vertical displacement did the earthquake produce at this location
這個地震在這個地方產生多少的垂直位移
This is after the 2004 Sumada Earthquake
這個就是在2004蘇門達大地震過後
Everyone can see that
大家可以看到就是說
All coral reefs are lifted above sea level
所有珊瑚礁都被抬到海平面以上
Then we can directly measure
然後我們就可以直接去量測
Because of the vertical displacement caused by the earthquake
因為這個地震所造成的垂直的位移
Then this is a coral reef to measure
那這個就是有珊瑚礁去量測
2005 scale 8.6
2005規模8.6
Vertical Displacement Caused by the Great Sumata Earthquake
在蘇門達大地震所造成的垂直的位移
The position of zero deformation is at this place
這個變形量零的位置在這個地方
Coral reefs from this line to the creek are all uplifted
這條線以溪珊瑚礁都是抬升的
The maximum lift is up to 2.5 meters
抬升最大量有到2.5米
Edom is offline
以東則是下線的
The largest drop is up to 1 meter
下升量最大的有到1米
That lift should be a good amount
那抬升的應該是很好量
But those who are offline may have to dive to measure
但是下線的可能就是要潛水去量
so do the work
所以做這些工作
In fact, as you can imagine, it is very hard work.
其實大家可以想像是很辛苦的
that apart from coral reef observation
那除了珊瑚礁觀測
We just could use this GPS
我們剛剛就是還可以用這個GPS
This is the global satellite positioning system
就是這個全球的衛星定位系統
To measure the coseismic displacement of the Banshui earthquake
去量測半水這個地震發生的這個同震的位移
For example, the red line
比如說紅色這個線
It was during the 2005 earthquake
就是在2005地震的時候
The displacement of the surface on both sides of it
它所兩側到的地表的位移量
The largest is actually nearly 4 meters
那最大事實上有將近有4米
Then with these observations
那有這些觀測量之後
Next we're going to see
接下來我們就是要去看說
How do we get from these surface observations
我們如何由這些地表的觀測資料
to understand the behavior of the fault's activity
去了解這個斷層的活動的行為
Then we can actually use a very simple theory
那我們其實可以用一個很簡單的理論
Let me explain to you
來跟大家做一個說明
It is a model of semi-wireless space
就是一個彈線半無線空間的模型
because assuming this is us
因為假設這個是我們
It is a deformed appearance observed on the surface
就是地表觀測到的一個變形的樣貌
Then scientists know that
然後科學家們知道說
Where might the underground fault be located?
地下的斷層可能在什麼位置
Then we know that
然後我們又知道說
on that fault
在那個斷層上面
If there is a dislocation of the unit on the fault of the unit
單位的斷層上面如果產生單位的錯動
anywhere on the earth
在地表上的任何一個地點
How big will be the horizontal and vertical differences
會產生的水平跟垂直非常會有多大
So our job is to find a combination
所以我們的工作就是去找一組組合
This combination actually has different forms of Huayi
這個組合事實上有不同的華宜的形態
Let's see how we can go
那看怎樣的方式可以去
Fitting Observations to the Surface
擬合地表的觀測結果
This is a reverse process
這就是一個逆推過程
Then we can go back to calculate
那我們就可以去反算
The Situation of Chinese Americans on the Fault Level
斷層面上華裔的情形
what about this
那這個呢
that we are first
就是我們首先就是
Need to know the geometry of the fault
需要知道斷層的幾何形貌
that fault geometry
那斷層幾何形貌
We can know from the distribution of earthquakes
我們就可以從地震的分布來得知
for example
譬如說
This is in the Sumata region
這個是在蘇門達地區的
A case of earthquake distribution
一個地震分布的情形
Then we will draw a profi
然後我們會畫一個profi
then we know
那我們就知道說
The distribution of this earthquake
這個地震分布的
distribution of a collection space
一個集合空間的分布
then we know
然後我們就知道
Possible Situation Angles of Faults
斷層的可能的情形角
For example, the latent layer may be slower
譬如說潛層可能比較緩
Humidity Deep places are steeper
濕度 深的地方比較陡
then we can
那我們就可以
Apply the geometry using this fault
應用使用這個斷層的幾何形貌
then calculate
然後去推算
The distribution of its ethnic Chinese on the fault level
在斷層面上它的華裔的分布
The red and yellow room is
那紅黃色間就是
The number of Chinese on this fault level
這個斷層面上的華裔量
projected onto the surface of a
投影到地表的一個
is a distribution
就是一個分布的情形
and black
然後黑色呢
is our observation
是我們的觀測值
that pink words
那個粉紅色的話
is the predicted value of our model
就是我們模型的預測值
then you can see this
那可以看到這個
In fact, the fit is pretty good.
其實吻合還蠻好的
then we know
那我們就知道說
In this 2005 earthquake
在這個2005的地震
its setback
它的挫動量
Nearly at least 12 meters of setback
將近至少有12米左右的挫動量
What about after the third?
那第三過後呢
Actually
其實呢
these have been
這些已經
Many of these book exhibitions in this disaster area
這個災區的很多這些冊展
in fact there will be
事實上也會有
There will also be a situation of continuous motion
還會有持續運動的一個情形
That's mainly because some energy
那主要是因為有些能量
Not fully released during the earthquake
在地震的時候沒有完全被釋放出來
So it will have a case of actively moving
所以它會有積極移動的一個情形
For example, in this Raiva book exhibition
譬如說在這個拉伊瓦這個冊展
This is the time of the earthquake
這個是地震的時間
After that earthquake you can find that it has a
那地震過後你可以發現它有一個
A variation of the direct decay
直速衰減的一個變化
very strong change
很強烈的一個變化
Then finally stabilized slowly
然後最後才慢慢的再穩定下來
slower again
速度再變得比較慢
then this is
然後這個是
Beeson's book exhibition
Beeson這個冊展
with Samp
跟Samp
it has the same
它都有同樣
That is, it will deform rapidly after the earthquake
就是在地震過後它會有快速的變形
Then slowly it will return to
然後慢慢的它就會回到
It is at the speed of deformation before the earthquake
就是地震前變形的這個速度上
This is the so-called exact deformation
這是所謂的正好變形
Then we will introduce to you
那接下來我們就是會跟大家介紹一下
It is this screen bag near Taiwan
就是台灣臨近的這個螢幕袋
This is the structure of a ground near the screen strip in Taiwan
這是臺灣臨近螢幕帶的一個地體的架構
Because Taiwan is located at the junction of the Eurasian plate and the Philippine Sea plate
因為臺灣是位於歐亞大陸板塊跟菲兵海板塊的交接處
Off the northeastern coast of Taiwan, the Philippine Sea Plate follows the Ryeball Trench
在臺灣的東北部外海 菲兵海板塊沿著流球海溝
Then the screen goes under the Eurasian plate
然後螢幕到歐亞大陸板塊下面
To the south is the Eurasian plate along the Mara Trench
南邊則是歐亞大陸板塊 沿著馬拉海溝
Screen to the bottom of the Philippine Binghai plate
螢幕到菲兵海板塊下面
Then the heavy bone fault in eastern Taiwan is the wind and belt of these two plates
然後臺灣東部的重骨斷層就是這兩個板塊的風和帶
To the east of the heavy bone fault is the Philippine Sea plate
在重骨斷層以東是屬於菲兵海板塊
To the west is the Eurasian plate
以西則是屬於歐亞大陸板塊
Because Taiwan's rate of plate aggregation in this place
因為臺灣在這個地方板塊聚合的速率
In fact, it can be as high as 90 meters on average
其實可以高達有90米米的平均
Then in the south and north are the main screens
然後在南邊跟北邊是螢幕為主
In the middle is the collision
中間則是以碰撞為主
So Taiwan will have a mountain with a height of nearly 4 kilometers
所以臺灣會有將近有4千米的高山
It's here that in fact it's collision-based
就是在這邊事實上它是以碰撞為主
Next to it, there are actually two very large screen strips
旁邊呢 事實上有兩個非常大的螢幕帶
So we have to evaluate
所以呢 我們就必須要去評估
Will there be a big screen with earthquakes near Taiwan in the future?
將來在台灣臨近是不是會有大的一個螢幕帶地震會發生
So what is this? Over the past 100 years?
那這是呢 過去一百年來呢
Some Major Earthquakes Near Taiwan
台灣附近一些主要的地震
Then here are some earthquakes with the scale of Six Flags
那這邊列出規模六根旗的一些地震
Then the color represents the depth of the earthquake
然後顏色代表是地震發生的深度
Then the bigger the earthquake the bigger the circle
然後地震越大 它的圈圈就越大
What about the past hundred years?
那過去一百年來呢
The main earthquake can be seen off the coast of Ryukyu
可以看到主要地震發生在琉球外海
with the eastern seas of Taiwan
跟台灣東部外海
There were also some big earthquakes on that land
那陸地上也有一些大的地震
But compared with the earthquakes in the Ryukyu Sea Country, there are relatively few
但相跟琉球海國這邊的地震比相較而言就是比較少
The largest earthquake was a magnitude 7.7 earthquake in 1920
那最大地震是1920年一個規模7.7的地震
Near Lake Ryukyu
在琉球島湖附近
Are there some tsunami events near Taiwan?
那在台灣附近是不是有一些海嘯事件
that's true
那也的確是有的
Because Japanese scholars have investigated some
因為日本學者呢 他們調查一些
Some information on the lake on Ryukyu Island
琉球島湖上面的一些資料
found in 1771
發現在1771年
This year, in fact, the subsurface layer of the Ryukyu Trench may have a rupture of the subsurface layer.
今年呢事實上這個琉球海溝的潛層可能產生一個潛層的一個破裂
Generating a Turtle Baa Earthquake
產生一個龜膜八阿地震
In fact, the Kameo Hachia earthquake was
那這個龜膜八阿地震事實上在
caused these tsunamis to be seen near these islands
就造成這些島嶼附近看到這些海嘯
The height of the tsunami was actually more than 30 meters
那海嘯的高度事實上有超過30米
So it's actually pretty impressive
所以事實上是蠻可觀的
Then there is the Mara Trench
那另外就是馬拉海溝
The Mara Trench actually extends to the south of Taiwan to the Philippines
那馬拉海溝呢事實上是在台灣的南邊一直延伸到這個菲兵
That's because Luzon was colonized by Spain in the 17th century
那因為呂宋呢在17世紀就已經被西班牙殖民
Then we read in the past
那過去我們翻閱
It is the data of these past histories
就是過去這些歷史的資料
In fact, for the past 400 years he
事實上他過去400年來
There is no earthquake in this hidden vine belt
並沒有在這個隱蔓帶並沒有發生龜膜大魚八的地震
But will it happen in the future
但是呢將來會不會發生
In fact, there is a lot of uncertainty
其實是有很很大不確定型的
Just like the 2004 Sumatra earthquake
就跟這個2004蘇門達阿地震一樣
The Sumada earthquake, the earthquake in that place started online
這個蘇門達阿地震它那個地方的這個地震的在線走起呢
In fact, about a thousand years ago
事實上是大概是千年左右
So what do you say in this
那所以說呢在這個
Although this place has not had a major earthquake in the past 400 years
這個地方雖然它過去四百年沒有發生大地震
But we cannot rule out that it will not have a major earthquake in the future
但是我們不能排除說它在未來不會發生大地震
So we still have to study some deformation behaviors in this place
所以我們還是得要去研究這個地方的一些變形的行為
Then let's introduce the Ryukyu Trench first.
那我們先介紹一下這個琉球海溝
Because the Ryukyu Trench is relatively tight
因為琉球海溝是比較緊
This is what happened when the earthquake collapsed off the coast of northeastern Taiwan
這個是在台灣東北部外海地震崩潰的情形
Lighter colors are shallower earthquakes
比較淺色系是比較淺層的地震
Deeper is a deeper earthquake
比較深是比較深的地震
so you can see what the screen does
所以你可以看到螢幕作用
if we go from here
如果我們從這個地方
This is an instant noodle from the Ryukyu Trench
這個是琉球海溝拉一個泡面
You can see the distribution of these earthquakes generated by the plate screen
你可以看到板塊螢幕產生的這些地震的分布
Then we can use these in eastern Taiwan
那我們就可以用台灣東部這些
Velocity yields of crustal deformation observed on land
陸地上觀測到的地殼變形的速度產
to calculate is to say
去計算就是說
Will there be a major earthquake in this place in the future?
將來這個地方會不會發生大地震
if it had a big earthquake
如果它發生大地震的話
what its possible ruptured form looks like
它可能的破裂形式是什麼樣子
the magnitude of the earthquake it can produce
它可能產生的地震規模的大小事
what a situation
怎麼樣一個情形
Because our strategy is all on land
因為我們的這個策戰都是在陸地上
So in fact we can probably say that
所以事實上我們大概可以知道說
closer to the coast
比較靠近海岸的地方
It's actually possible for energy to build up here
它事實上 能量事實上是有可能在這邊積聚的
But we have no way to speculate that
但是我們沒有辦法去推測說
How long will its rupture range extend?
到底它這個破裂範圍會延伸到多長
The reference here is mainly to refer to the distribution of earthquakes.
那我們這邊所參考主要是參考地震的分布
Because now is the flow of the last generation
因為在就是以末代這個流
Between the Peaceful Basin and the Nahai Basin
在和平海盆到拿海盆之間
There is a very dense earthquake bill
有一個非常密集的地震的條單
So we think the area where it broke may be this area
所以我們認為它破裂的區域可能是這個區域
According to some empirical formulas of seismologists
那根據地震學家的一些經驗公式
We know the likely rupture area of ​​an earthquake
我們知道地震可能的破裂面積
Let's say the length is 120 kilometers
譬如說這個長度是120公里
Then the width is 70 km
然後寬度是70公里
then we can calculate its earthquake size
那我們就可以計算它的地震規模
Probably around 7.5 to 8
大概是可能7.5到8左右
But if we use another method
但是如果我們用另外一個方法
Assume that the earthquakes here have a period of 1500 years
假設這邊的地震在實現週期1500年
Then it was broken into a loss rate of 86 meters.
然後斷成虧損率是86米米一二
The largest scale is 8.6
最大的規模就是8.6
The largest scale mentioned here means
那這邊講的最大規模就是說
All the energy accumulated here
所有累積在這邊的能量
Released once by an earthquake
經由地震一次釋放出來
Of course, if it has many earthquakes
當然如果說它有很多次的地震
release these energies slowly
慢慢去釋放這些能量
Then maybe it won't be this big
那也許這個規模就不會這麼大
will be smaller
就會再更小一點
So let's use this cracked paper model to see
那我們就使用這個破裂紙模型去看看
If such an earthquake occurs in this place
如果這樣地震發生在這個地方
what kind of behavior
會產生什麼樣的一個行為
good
好
please wait
請大家等待一下
Okay, this is the model we just used
好 這個就是用我們剛剛那個模型
to calculate
去計算
If the earthquake happened
如果說這個地震發生了
what harm will it do
那它會產生什麼樣的危害
here represents this
這邊代表是這個
The velocity of a positive wave passing through a
正波傳遞的一個的速度
Then this side represents the wave height generated by the tsunami
然後這邊代表是海嘯產生的波高
then you can see
那你可以看到
The seismic waves of this tsunami travel first
這個海嘯的地震波先傳
The tsunami was generated after the transmission
傳過之後海嘯才產生
And then this tsunami will do a lot of damage all over the east coast
然後這個海嘯會在整個東部海岸造成很大的危害
The maximum breaking height can reach about 4 meters
最大的破高可以到4米左右
You can see this is
大家可以看到這個是
The shooting range is about 2 meters to 4 meters
射階大概是2米到4米左右
along this eastern coast
沿著這個東部的海岸
In fact, there are quite a few changes
事實上都有滿大的一些變化
And what about the tsunami?
然後海嘯呢
Ship bypassing Taiwan to the Taiwan Strait
繞過台灣往台灣海峽船
A case of boat waves
船波的一個情形
and what about the east
然後東部呢
There is still some back and forth
還持續有一些來回的
Because of the back and forth shock of the tsunami waves
因為海嘯波來回的震盪
Then what
然後呢
can see this
可以看到這個
In fact there are almost 2 to 4 meters of some
事實上將近有2到4米的一些
Brogao will clean these places
破高會有清洗這些地方
then go around
然後就繞過去
to the Taiwan Strait
傳到台灣海峽這邊
That's because the main rupture direction of this earthquake
那因為這個地震主要破裂方向
is the direction of the Pacific Ocean
是往太平洋的方向
So in fact, for western Taiwan,
所以事實上對於台灣西部的話
Its harm is less obvious
它的危害就比較不是那麼的顯著
but in the east
但是在東部的話
In fact its impact is quite significant
事實上它的影響是滿顯著的
This is probably a tsunami boat
這個大概就是一個海嘯船
Situation of transmission
傳播的情形
This is what our earth
這是由我們地球所
Provided by Li Xianzhong Associate Research Institute
李憲中副研究研究所提供的
next we will see
接下來我們就要看
us
我們
how do scientists know
科學家如何知道就是
Has there ever been a tsunami in this place?
這個地方是不是有曾經發生過海嘯
how do we study these tsunamis
我們怎麼去研究這些海嘯
older events of these tsunamis
比較老的這些海嘯的事件
There are several methods
主要有幾個方法
For example we can go
譬如說我們可以去
these seaside to do some
這些海邊去做一些
sampling work
取樣的工作
To see the distribution of these grades
去看這些成績物的分布
then go see say
然後去看看說
Is this related to the tsunami?
這是不是跟海嘯
Tsunami-related grades
海嘯相關的成績物
otherwise we can go to the beach
另外的話我們可以去海邊
Find these very large boulders
找尋這些非常大的石塊
Because such a large rock
因為這麼大的石塊
it's no way through that
它是沒有辦法經過就是
It's just that these waves go
就是平常這些海浪去
move to shore
搬動到岸邊來
Usually it's ten dollars
通常這麼大十塊的話
or typhoon
要嘛就是颱風
Or a tsunami
要嘛就是海嘯
to be transported to the coast
才能搬運到海岸邊來
So scientists can go and find
所以科學家們就可以去採尋
just to collect some
就是去採集一些
some samples for dating
一些研樣去做定年
Then learned that he was relocated to
然後知道他被搬遷到
The terrain of this coast
這個海岸邊的地勢
then go and see say
然後再去看看說
Is he with some
他是不是跟一些
Events that implicitly bring about earthquakes are related
隱默帶來地震的事件是有關的
what about other than that
那除此之外呢
It is to rely on historical documents to record now
就是要靠歷史文現在記錄
For example, Taiwan
譬如說台灣呢
There are also some records of tsunamis
也有一些海嘯記錄
Most definitely dated to 1867
目前最確定的是在1867年
in Keelung?
在基隆呢
There was once a tsunami event
曾經發生過一次海嘯的事件
There are some historical records over here
那這邊有一些歷史文獻的記載
Then everyone can take a look
那大家可以看一下
that's the reaction here
就是這邊的反應
That is to say, the water in the port recedes
就是說港口的海水後退
until all the fish move in mud or water
直到所有的魚在泥地或水跟如動
struggle with
跟掙扎
And what about these fathers, daughters and children?
然後這些父女跟小孩呢
just go and run
就趕快去跑去
to examine this baby's gift
去檢視這個幼人的禮物
Then what
然後呢
The results of it
結果呢
What about sea water?
海水呢
first back
先先退
A very important feature of a tsunami is that the sea water will recede first
海嘯有個很重要的特徵就是海水會先往後退
and then it will come back
然後接下來它就會再回來
And when you come back, the height is very high
而且就回來那個高度就很高
Then there will be a great disaster
然後就會造成很大的災害
Then this world is recorded in historical documents
那這個世上在歷史文獻上是有記載的
That except in this English literature
那除了在這個英文的文獻
The world is made in Tamsui Hall
世上在淡水廳制
And there are records in the world
而世上也有記載
That is to say, there were some tsunami incidents at that time
就是說那個時候有一些海嘯的事件
Then hundreds of people died like this
然後死了好幾百人這樣子
Then we can also learn from these historical Christian districts
那我們也可以從這些歷史的基督區
Find records of these tsunamis
找到這些海嘯的記錄
Then we based on the description of these historical documents
然後我們再根據這些歷史文獻的描述
Go see this site where these tsunamis have occurred in the past
去看看過去這些發生海嘯的這個地點
where is it now
它是現今的什麼地方
Then we make it beautiful
然後我們就把它俊化出來
Then slowly go to find
然後慢慢的再去找尋說
what was the source of the possible tsunami
可能的海嘯的源頭是什麼造成的
besides these
那除了這些呢
Like the archaeological team of Academia Sinica and National Taiwan University in Keelung North
像中研院跟台大的考古團隊在基隆河北
They just do some research on cultural chairs
他們就做一些文化椅子的調查
Then they found out during their investigation that
然後他們在調查當中就發現說
Like this Uni3 this
像這個Uni3這個
this grade level
這個成績層
it's a walrus
它是一個比較海象的
high-concentration water-like
高濃度水流般運的
formed by an accumulation
一個堆積作用所形成
So maybe it has something to do with the tsunami
所以可能是跟海嘯是有關係的
So scientists can actually do
所以科學家們事實上也可以做
Grass hook
挖草鉤
Then go to the source of these grades
然後去看這些成績物的來源
and then speculate that
然後去推測說
what grades
哪些的成績物
Maybe it's related to the tsunami
可能跟海嘯是有關的
Those same technologies are in fact
那相同的這些技術事實上
can also be used for this
也可以用於這個
Some of the inbound faults
入境商斷層的一些
repeat cycle
重複周期
The response cycle is a
回復周期的是一個
some studies like this
一些研究這樣子
Then we introduce this
那接下來我們介紹這個
after the ryukyu screen bag
琉球螢幕袋之後
Next we're going to look at Mara Screen Bags
接下來我們要看馬拉螢幕袋
That mara screen bag in fact
那馬拉螢幕袋事實上
In fact, it is quite far from Taiwan.
離台灣事實上是比較遠
yes
沒錯
It actually starts from the south of Taiwan
它事實上從台灣南邊
stretches all the way to luzon
一直延伸到呂宋
But should we pay attention to it
但是我們需不需要關注它
we really need to pay attention to it
我們是真的要關注它
Because if a relatively large rupture tsunami occurs here,
因為這邊如果產生比較大的破裂海嘯
just go this way
就直接往這邊船
If the boat over here
那這邊船的話
will cause mainland China
就會造成大陸中國
Vietnam on the southeast coast
東南沿海越南
Then many countries in Southeast Asia
然後東南亞很多國家
will be implicated
都會受到牽連
What about the tsunami, hit it and bounce back
那海嘯呢 打過去再反彈回來
For those who dive into the sea in the west of Taiwan
對台灣西部這些潛海的這些
These are the cities on the coast
就是在鄰岸邊的這些城市
In fact, there will be some great influence
事實上也會有很大的一些影響
Then everyone can see that
那大家可以看到說
This plate goes to the river data to follow in Taiwan
這邊板塊去河數據跟在台灣
A little more than here near Taiwan
比台灣 附近這邊還要再多一點
About 92 mimiteps one or two
大概是92個米米特普一二
In addition to this place
那這個地方除了有這個
This big one with foam
以沫帶的這個大的這個
big this drowning fault
大的這個溺斷層
It actually also has a
它事實上也有一個
In the Philippines there is a large this China fault
在菲兵有一個大型的這個走華斷層
Philippine fault
是菲兵斷層
Then this fault is also a
那這個斷層也是一個
A very dangerous fault
蠻危險的一個斷層
Then let's focus on this today
那我們今天就先focus在這個
Mala shadow tape
馬拉影沫帶
Then this is across this shadow foam belt
那這個是跨過這個影沫帶
The distribution of earthquakes
地震分佈的情形
That color represents the depth of different earthquakes
那顏色代表是不同地震的深度
The red ones are relatively shallow earthquakes
比較紅色是比較淺層的地震
Then the blue purple is a deeper earthquake
然後藍色紫色是比較深的一些地震
That's different profi
那這是不同的profi
Then I took 3 to 5 today
那我今天取了3到5
Let me show you these instant noodles
這幾個泡麵給大家看一下
You can clearly see this
大家可以清楚的看到這個
Shadow Foam's Angle
影沫的角度
slowly change
慢慢的變斗
In fact, it has turned into a collision effect here.
到這邊事實上就已經轉成碰撞的作用
In fact our earth
事實上我們地球所
As long as in 1996, in fact, a lot of observation work has been done in Brigade
只要在1996年事實上就已經在旅送做很多觀測的工作
This picture is from about 20 years ago
這張圖是大概過去將近有20年來
We did some GPS work over here
我們在這邊做了一些GPS的一些工作
This is the GPS level speed we obtained
這是我們求得到的GPS水平的速度廠
Relative to this point the velocity of the factory
相對於這個點的速度廠
This is the vertical speed factory
這邊是垂直的速度廠
We use these GPS observations
我們就是利用這些GPS觀測
Let's reverse the distribution of Chinese on this fault line
我們去反推這個斷層上的華裔的分布
This is the result we got
這是我們得到的結果
We can get a so-called plate of Orheb
我們可以得到一個所謂的板塊的Orheb
Plate Orheb it's actually a fault rate for Chinese descent
板塊Orheb它其實是斷層華裔的虧損率
Divided by the long-term Chinese rate
除以長期的華裔速率
So if this value is higher
所以如果這個值越高
Represents the growing likelihood of a major rupture
代表相來越有可能發生大的破裂
if smaller
如果越小的話
It is safer in comparison
相較就是比較安全的
So we have provided two models here
所以我們這邊有提供兩個模型
blue represents
藍色代表是
Faults are usually in the state of creeping
斷層平常是屬於潛移的狀態
So keep releasing energy
所以一直在釋放能量
is a relatively safe state
是一個相對比較安全的狀態
the red area
那紅色的區域
This means it belongs to a locked state
這代表它是屬於一個鎖住的狀態
That is to say, a big earthquake in the future
就是說將來大地震
It is possible for a relatively large rupture
它有可能發生比較大的破裂
that black arrow
那這個黑色的箭頭
It means that when an earthquake occurs in the future
就代表說將來地震發生的時候
These curations of the possible surface
可能地表的這些策展
a way of movement
運動的一個方式
Then we can use these
那我們就可以由這些
surface data area to invert
地表的資料區去反轉
In fact, our model
那其實我們這個模型
because we entered the trench
因為我們進海溝
In fact it's not obvious
事實上沒有很明顯
Not a good few observation points
沒有很好的一些觀測點
So in fact we're near the trench
所以說事實上我們靠近海溝附近
Our model resolution
我們的模型解析度
actually not very good
其實並不是很好的
Therefore, in addition to making observations on land,
因此我們除了在陸地上做觀測
In fact, we also have to go
其實我們也必須要去
Observing these behaviors of these deformations on the seabed
觀測海床上的這些變形的這些行為
Then I will introduce
那接下來我就會介紹一下
The way our planet is going to develop now
我們現在地球所要發展的方法
The first one is sea floor geodesy.
那第一個就是海底大地測量
The seabed geodesy is actually
那海底大地測量其實它就是
Integrated GPS satellite positioning system
結合的全球黨衛星定位系統
Positioning with deep wave
跟深波定位
For example, we have to be on the seabed
譬如說我們就必須在海床上
place these deep wave transponders
擺放這些深波的回應器
Then we go out with fishing boats
然後我們出去就是用漁船
We will put these GPS on the fishing boat
漁船上面我們會擺放這些GPS
these observatories
這些觀測站
Then what
然後呢
This fishing boat compared to
這漁船相對於
The location of any GPS point on land
陸地上任何的一個GPS點的位置
You can use the commonly used dynamic positioning
可以用一般我們常用的動態定位
to get
去得到
what about
那至於呢
fishing boats on the seabed
漁船到這個海床上面的
relative position
相對的位置
It is to use deep wave positioning to obtain
就是用深波定位去求取
In this way we can know that
這樣子我們就可以去知道就是
any point on the seabed
海床上任何一點
Ways of motion relative to land
相對陸地上的運動的方式
what about now
那目前呢
we are on the ground
我們在地
On our planet we now have two proving grounds
我們地球我們現在有兩個試驗場
One is in the far south of the Okinawa tide
一個是在沖繩海潮的南遠
The water depth is about 1300 meters
那水深大約是1300米
The other one is in Ryukyu
另外一個就是在琉球
Near the Ryukyu Trench
靠近琉球海溝附近
The water depth is about 3800 meters
水深大約是3800米左右
Then this study is actually a
那這個研究其實是一個
It takes a lot of time and money to research
很花時間經歷跟經費的研究
because we have to observe
因為我們必須要觀測
long enough for some good
夠久時間才會有一些好的
Research results can come out
研究成果可以出來
What does the deep wave responder look like
深波回應器長的樣子
Throw these instruments into the sea
那這些儀器丟到海裡面去
it is not recyclable
就不可回收了
So we have to be in
所以說我們就必須要在
Before the battery runs out
這個電池還沒有耗水完之前
Do research every year as much as possible
盡可能的每年去做研究
Then get the most of these observations
然後獲取最多的這些觀測的資料
That's the case with our Offshore Instrumentation Department.
那這是我們海上儀器部方的情形
And then we also have to measure the seawater
然後另外我們也必須要去量測海水
compare its conductivity
比較潛沉它的導電度
parameters such as temperature and pressure
溫度跟壓力這些參數
Because when we are doing deep wave positioning
因為我們在做深波定位的時候
The speed at which this deep wave travels
這個深波傳遞的速度
are related to these parameters
跟這些參數都有關係
So we also have to measure the relevant
所以我們也必須要去量測相關的
These physical parameters
這些物理參數
Then it's time to do our positioning
然後來做我們定位的時候
do some commissioning
去做一些交準
That's when doing research
那這是在做研究的時候
In some states using various transfer funds
在使用各種不同的傳資的一些狀態
In fact, doing this research is also very hard.
那其實做這個研究也是很辛苦
Because it is mainly because of the signal of the deep wave
因為主要是因為深波的這個訊號
it will be affected by the sound of the engine on this boat
它會受到這個船上引擎聲的
So usually we're doing
所以通常我們在做
when doing this research
做這個研究的時候
Just drive the boat to our target area
就是把船開到我們的目標區
Then turn off the engine and start drifting
然後就把引擎關掉開始漂流
And then everyone is on 24-hour shifts
然後所有人就是要24小時的輪班
and then go record those signals
然後去記錄這些訊號
So what we usually do is
所以我們通常做這個就是
24 hours is a shift, you have to go all the time
24小時是輪班要一直去
Constantly read data
不斷讀取的資料
and what about the staff
然後工作人員呢
have to endure the harsh working environment on board
又要忍受船上惡劣的工作環境
Because basically Taiwan's research ships are too sought-after
因為基本上台灣的研究船太搶手了
So we generally have to follow the general
所以我們一般要跟一般的
do ocean these
做海洋這些
When researchers go to compete this ship schedule
研究人員去compete這個船期的時候
actually quite difficult
其實相當困難
In the end we all chose fishing boats
最後我們都是選擇漁船
There are many bugs on the fishing boat
漁船上面還有很多小蟲
So our colleagues often come back after
所以我們同事們常常回來之後
Usually his feet are covered with red bean ice
通常就是他的腳上都是紅豆冰
or lack of sleep
要不然就是睡眠不足
It's actually a hard job
其實是一個滿辛苦的工作
what they did in the past
他們過去世上做了
Nearly five years of research
將近有五年多的研究
It is not easy to finally have a comparison point
毫不容易終於有比觀測點
is now everyone sees this
就是現在大家看到這個
white this arrow
白色這個箭頭
It is this station exercise input field
是這個車站運動輸入場
Although it is only a station
雖然它只是一個站
but we for
但是我們為了
Collecting information on this site took a lot of effort
收集這個站資料花了很多的心理
Then we have another observatory that is
那我們還有另外一個觀測站是
This place closer to the trench
比較靠近海溝的這個地方
Then of course we do this research to see
那我們做這個研究當然就是想要去看
close to the trench
靠近海溝附近到底
This fault is continuously creeping
這個斷層是持續在潛移
or is it locked
還是它是鎖住的狀態
if it keeps creeping
如果它是持續潛移的話
that of course that is a good thing
那當然那是一件好事
That is, its energy is continuously released
就是它能量是持續釋放
but if it is locked
但是如果它是鎖住的話
still really
這樣還是真的要
some major settings
一些重大的設置
in fact it is
事實上就是
Can it be placed on the east coast
是不是能放在東海岸
Actually there are some
其實是有一些
some space to consider
需要考量的一些空間
Besides that we also
那除此之外我們也
The earth is like me, I also want to say
地球所像我本身我也想說
Set up the pressure level of this seabed
擺設這個海床的壓力級
Then this is the same as the seabed survey just now
那這跟剛剛的這個海底大力測量
are complementary
是互補的
Because if the seabed is measured vigorously,
因為海底大力測量的話
when you have to observe
就是你有去觀測的時候
will have information
才會有資料
If the seabed pressure level
那海床壓力級的話
itself is recyclable
它本身是可以回收的
I can leave it for half a year
我可以不放個半年
Then I have the data for half a year
那我就有這半年的資料
Then go and observe this
然後去觀測這個
deformation on the seabed
在海床上的變形
The principle of it is actually very simple
那它的原理其實是很簡單
it is in fact
它事實上是
measure the water
量測這個海水
Because if the seabed deforms
因為海床如果產生變形
Then the depth of the sea water measured by this instrument will change.
那這個儀器所涼測到這個海水的深度就會產生改變
Then what
然後呢
The pressure of the cold test will change
壓力 涼測的壓力就會產生改變
With this pressure difference, we can convert the deformation of Haishuang
那有這個壓力的差 我們就可以去換算海霜的變形量
for example this
譬如說這個
Let this line be the position before deformation, the position of Haishuang before deformation
核設這條線是變形前的位置 海霜變形前的位置
Green is the deformed position
綠色是變形後的位置
Then I can see the pressure difference before deformation and the pressure difference after deformation
然後呢 我就可以看這個變形前的壓差 跟變形後的壓差
Then guess how big the vertical deformation of this sea frost is
然後去推測呢 這個海霜垂直的變形是多大
That's usually 100 Pascale 100% change
那通常100個Pascale 100%的改變
Like a deformation of about 1 cm
像就是大概是1公分左右的一個變形量
So this instrument is very precise
所以這個儀器是非常精準的
Then we hope that in the future we can cross the Ryukyu Trench to set up these instruments
那我們希望將來可以再跨過琉球海溝去擺設這些儀器
Then go to see some deformation behaviors near the Ryukyu Trench
然後去看看近琉球海溝附近的一些變形的一些行為
OK, let's wrap things up a little bit.
好 那我們稍微要總結一下
Today we introduced several different methods to observe the deformation of the screen strip
我們今天就是介紹了幾個不同的方法去觀測螢幕帶的變形
For example, there is this land
譬如說有這個大地的
GNSS
用全球導航衛星系統
Synthetic Aperture Interferometric Radar
合成孔鏡 干涉雷達
There's also a large ocean basin survey and a seabed piezometer.
還有海底大池測量 和海床壓力計
We can go and observe the displacement of the surface
我們可以去觀測地表的位移
Estimation of the fault's Chinese tree rate
推估斷層的華裔樹率
and assess its potential future earthquake location
跟評估它未來可能發生地震的位置
with the scale
跟規模
If we want to know more distant events
如果我們想要知道比較久遠的事件
we can use sea connection
我們就可以利用海接
Or use the depth of the coral reef
或是用珊瑚礁的台深的歷程
to see these older earthquake events
去看這些比較老的地震的事件
tsunami words
海嘯的話
We can go to see the tsunami's results
我們就可以去看海嘯的成績物
or a large boulder on the coast
或是海岸邊的很大的石塊
Or look up some historical literature records
或者去查詢一些歷史的文獻記錄
To guess where the tsunami might occur
去推測海嘯可能發生的位置
The source of its corresponding tsunami
跟它對應的海嘯的源頭
Or the relationship with the earthquake on the screen
或者跟螢幕帶地震的關係
We also introduce
我們也跟大家介紹一下
The way the screen strips the crust deforms
螢幕帶地殼變形的方式
During the block screen process
在板塊螢幕的過程當中
before the earthquake
在地震發生之前
The upper plate will slowly arch
上部板塊會慢慢拱起
then move to land
然後往陸地方向移動
then after the earthquake
然後地震發生後
it will generate dive
它就會產生下潛
Then move towards the sea
然後往海的方向運動
Then we introduce
然後我們跟大家介紹一下
That is, Huayi will be distributed everywhere on the fault
就是在斷層上華宜隨身都會分布
before the earthquake
在地震發生之前
Energy slowly in the depths of the fault
能量慢慢在斷層的深處
accumulate slowly
慢慢的累積
Then this may take hundreds to thousands of years
然後這個可能需要累積百年到千年
But when the earthquake happened
但是這個地震發生的時候
maybe 20 seconds to 30 seconds
就可能是20秒到30秒
It can accumulate the past from hundreds to thousands of years
它就可以把過去累積百年到千年的
These energies are released
這些能量釋放出來
Therefore, there will be a large
因此就會產生很大的
Rule shifts on these surfaces
這些地表的統政位移
If after the earthquake
如果地震過後
In some places the energy has not been fully released
有些地方能量還沒有完全被釋放出來
then after the earthquake
然後在地震後
It will last this Huayi
它還會持續的這個華宜
Then our Taiwan is now located in this place
那我們台灣現在是位在這個地方
So let's study these screen strips now
那我們現在研究這些螢幕帶
is actually very important
其實是很重要的
because the screen has words
因為螢幕帶的話
For example, we study the Malayan Trench
譬如說我們研究馬來拉海溝
Then this is different from the Ryukyu Trench
那這跟琉球海溝不一樣
Because if the Ryukyu Trench ruptures,
因為琉球海溝如果產生破裂的話
Its main energy is to
它主要的能量是往
The direction of the Pacific
這個太平洋的方向傳
but if
但是如果
If a rupture occurs in the Mara Trench
馬拉海溝產生破裂的話
It actually goes to the South China Sea
它事實上就是往南海
Spread it to mainland China and the Indochina Peninsula
往中國大陸跟中南半島這邊傳
So it's pretty obvious that it could actually be a disaster.
所以它事實上可能造成災害是蠻顯著的
So we are in Taiwan
所以說我們在台灣
We near do these implicit bands with these observations
我們附近做這些隱默帶這些觀測
In fact, these experiences we can all
這些經驗事實上我們都可以
pass to these Southeast Asian countries
pass給這些東南亞國家
then if we are here
那如果我們在這個地方
There are some better monitoring
有一些比較好的監測
Assessment of Earthquake Hazards for the Whole Region
對這整個區域性的地震災害的評估
In fact, it has a considerable contribution to prevention.
跟預防事實上是有蠻大的貢獻
In addition, we actually
那另外就是我們其實
Attached to many of these in Taiwan
在台灣附設很多這些
Mimi Mama's GPS Observation Station
咪咪麻麻的GPS觀測站
Besides these observatories are used to do these
那這些觀測站除了用來做這些
scientific research
科學的研究
Earthquakes used to study the silent zone
用來研究隱默帶的地震
In fact, it has a lot of added value
其實它還有很多附加的價值
For example, we actually
譬如說我們其實
These GPS Observation Stations in Taiwan
台灣這些GPS觀測站
we can study some
我們可以研究一些
The movement of these landslides in Taiwan
台灣的這些山崩的運動
For example, this is near Mount Lu
譬如說這就是在盧山附近
Some GPS time series we set up
我們所設的一些GPS時間序列
Coordinates change over time
坐標隨時間改變
This is from 2005 to 2014
這是從2005年到2014年
basic data
基礎造資料
This is the east-west and vertical components of the north-south component
這是南北分量的東西分量跟垂直分量
we can see
我們就可以看到
when it rains heavily
在下大雨的時候
The process of slope rising into landslide sliding
邊坡升成山崩滑動的過程
We want to use this information
我們希望利用這些資料
To learn about the mechanism of these landslides
去了解一下這些山崩發生的機子
Is there any relationship between landslide sliding speed and rainfall?
到底山崩滑動速度跟降雨是不是有關係
Are there any signs before the landslide slides?
山崩滑動之前是不是有一些徵兆
These can be observed from the surface
這些都可以由地表的觀測
do some inversion
去做一些逆推
To understand the physical properties of landslide sliding surfaces
去了解到山崩滑動面上的物理性質
Also see
另外可以看到
In fact, there are places in the landslide area that will still rise
其實在山崩的地區有地方還是會抬升
Let's say it's a slope
譬如說這是一個邊坡
In fact you can see
事實上你可以看到
What you see is that it's an upward movement
看到的是它是一個往上升的運動
everyone will feel
大家一定會覺得
Why Landslides Shouldn't Be
為什麼山崩不是應該
everything slides down
所有東西都往下滑
why is it elevated
為什麼它會是抬升
Mainly it is at the stop of landslides
主要它是在山崩的止步
So it's a relatively quiet area
所以它是一個比較沉寂的區域
So this place is a rising
所以這個地方反而是一個上升的
a deformation
一個變形
So in fact if we can have some dense observations
所以我們事實上如果可以有一些密集的觀測
We can also generate landslides or dive into landslides
我們也可以對生成山崩或潛成山崩
There are some nice constraints
有蠻好的一些約制
What are the benefits of the geophysical method?
那地球物理的方法好處在哪裡
Mainly because of the geophysical method
主要是因為地球物理的方法
Our instruments are placed in the submerged or above the surface
我們的儀器就擺在潛沉或者是地表上面
When traditional civil engineering is doing landslide monitoring
那傳統土木在做山崩監測的時候
they have to specialize
他們就必須要專口
Then go set up the inclinometer
然後去擺設傾斜儀
But everyone can know that
但是大家可以知道就是說
if in a very active place
如果在一個很活躍的地方
that landslide
那山崩運
landslide transport it is the effect of gravity
山崩運它是重力的作用
So it's always slipping
所以它本身是一直在潛移的
then you can think of
那大家可以想到
If that it places everything after that hole is cut
如果那個它擺放一切那個孔被剪斷之後
In fact it would have to make a new hole
事實上它就必須要專一個新的孔
So now a one-meter brick neck costs about 8,000 yuan
那以現在一米的磚頸大概需要八千塊
as you can imagine
大家可以想像
The entire hillside must be moved up
整支一個山坡是要上移的
For example, spending 200 million to 300 million yuan in Lisanping
譬如說在離三坪花兩億到三億的經費
Then whole the slope
再整支這個邊坡
But because this slope is very active
但是因為這個邊坡很活躍
Then this is a decorative instrument
那這個當作裝飾的儀器
It's all unusable now
現在已經全部都不能用
Then if using this geophysical method
那如果使用這個地球物理的方法
The way we use these observations is in fact
我們用這些觀測的手法事實上
we can
我們就可以
Can be detected by non-destructive methods
可以用非破壞性的方法去檢測
Whether it's diving, it's scattered movement
不論是潛程 則散破運動
or these activities at the deep end
或是深層 端層的這些活動
can do it all
都可以來做
Alternatively, we can also
另外的話就是我們也可以
Do some assessment of water resources
對水資源做一些評估
For example we see
譬如說我們看到的
We have some consecutive
我們有一些連續的
These GPS stations
這些GPS觀測站
Then we can see
然後我們可以看到
For example, in the vertical
譬如說在垂直上
it has some obvious
它有很明顯的一些
agglomeration of changes
集結性的變化
it goes up and down
它會上上下下
It Long term will have a coupon
它Long term會有一個券
It's about, maybe about the Tectonic
是跟 可能是跟Tectonic有關
But there will be some fluctuations in its build-up
但它集結性上會有一些波動
those fluctuations
那這些波動
It's actually the groundwater below.
其實是跟下面的地下水
Or it is related to the amount of cold water in the soil
或跟土體的寒水量是有關係的
Then we can actually use
那我們事實上也可以用
It's our GPS
就是我們GPS
into these collective governments
進入到這些集結性的政府
to calculate in these soils
去反算在這些土體裡面
amount of cold water
寒水量的多寡
Then for this entire
然後對這個整個
Regional Water Resources Assessment
區域性的水資源評估
actually helps
事實上是有一些幫助的
the last one is
那最後一張就是
We do a lot of work in travel
我們在旅送做很多工作
This is our trip to send in 2009
這是我們09年到旅送
Then when we went over there to set up the station
然後我們去那邊佈站的時候
this is an elementary school
這是一個小學
everyone is very very nice
大家都非常非常的好
why we do this
為什麼我們要做這件事情
So we are laying out while
所以我們在佈設同時
Also explain to these children
也跟這些小朋友去解釋
The purpose of our observation
我們做這個觀測的目的
so this is actually quite interesting
所以這其實是蠻有趣的
we are there
就是我們就現場
Tell them about our work
跟他們介紹一下我們的工作
And then use it to nurture their next generation
然後也藉此培育他們這個下一代
Okay, thank you
好 謝謝
Okay, thank you very much, Dr. Hsu
好 那非常謝謝許博士
give us a very good speech
給我們非常精采的演講
the rest of our time now
那我們現在剩下的時間
open to audience questions
就開放給各位觀眾提問
About the content of the speech
大家對於演講的內容
Which point would I like to have a deeper understanding of
哪一點希望能夠有更深的瞭解
Or think of some good suggestions
或者有想到一些什麼好的建議
or a problem
或者是問題
Please ask questions
都請大家踴躍的提問
Thanks
謝謝
I won't talk about big questions, please actively raise them
不會說大問題都請大家踴躍的提出
What about our sponsor today?
那我們今天主辦單位呢
Prepared some products
準備了一些離品
he now we have
他現在我們有
October of this year
今年現在十月份的
The two staff members of Scientist held him up
科學人雜誌這兩位工作人員把他舉起來
do we have 6 or 7
我們有6本還是7本
We can give it to the audience friends who asked questions in front of the head
我們可以送給頭前面幾位提問的觀眾朋友
we ask everyone to raise their hands right now
我們現在就請大家先舉手
there's a microphone in front of you
你前面有一個麥克風
so there's a switch that's the green switch
所以有一個開關那個綠色的開關
so when you can speak into the microphone
所以當你就可以對著麥克風發言
Is there anyone who wants to start
有沒有哪一位要開始
good lady
好這位女士
ask the professor
請教教授
We seem to be the one in the reputation zone
我們好像是在信譽區的那個
101 belongs to the earthquake zone, right?
101是屬於地震帶是不是
that said besides saying
那就說除了說
Is there anything beyond our possible detection
這個我們可能的偵測之外有沒有什麼可以
prevent it from happening to him thank you
預防不要讓他發生謝謝
So we know that means
所以我們知道就是說
If we're on the new TV if we make some
如果我們在新電視 如果我們做一些
After water injection, it will cause some local changes in India
注水之後會造成當地一些印第的改變
Will change the situation in the local Indy
會改變當地印第的狀況
then maybe
那也許呢
is to make the earthquake happen earlier or later
就是會讓地震提早發生或延後發生
but now what i think
但是現在就我所思
It should be difficult to artificially
應該很難用人為的方式
do some action
去做一些動作
so that this earthquake does not happen
讓這個地震不會發生
Yes it is more difficult
對 是比較困難
It would be better to find a way to take care of the house.
比較好的應該是想辦法把房子兼顧一點
This is actually in Canada they
這其實在加拿大他們
In western Canada they actually have a lot of oil and gas development
在加拿大西部他們事實上有很多油氣的開發
that's or something they'll pick
那或是一些他們要採的
They use some drip heat and he might have to pour water into it
他們用一些滴熱,他可能要注水進去
Then they found that when the water is injected, it will lead to life, that is, it will cause a lot of small droplet vibrations
那他們發現在注水的時候會引導生,就是會引發很多小滴震
What about these small droplet shocks, for some, are
那這些小滴震呢,對於某些,就是
He might just be an energy release character
他可能就是一個能量釋放的角色
But it's also possible that he'll make some of the fault zone's drip quake
但是他也有可能會讓某些斷層帶的滴震
It couldn't have happened so soon, it happened earlier
本來沒有這麼快發生,提早發生
So now when you intervene, some will be good and some will be bad
所以現在你做干預就是,會有的是好的,有的是不好的
It's hard for you to go because we don't know now
那你很難去,因為我們現在都不知道
fault his own coin is in what state
斷層他的本身硬幣是在什麼狀態
So you don't know if you're good or bad for the area after you do this movement
所以你不知道你做這個動作之後,你對這個區域是好的還是不好的
Yes, because some of them may have already crossed the boundary
對,因為有些他可能就是已經凌界的
All you need is a small trace, some changes in coins
你只要一個小小的trace的,硬幣的一些改變
You'll make him have a big tick
你就會讓他產生一個大的滴震
some if it's still far away, you might do something
那有些如果還很遠的話,你可能做一些動作
won't let him, just no, in fact he won't have any changes
就不會讓他,就是沒有,他事實上是不會有任何的一些變化
So this is actually because seismologists or earth dancers
所以這其實,因為地震學家或地球舞與學家
Now the biggest one, the problem is
現在最大一個,難題就是
for faulting his coin
因為斷層他的硬幣
In fact, we don't know the state of India on the fault.
斷層上面印利狀態其實我們是不曉得的
All we know is that the earthquake happened and India will change
我們只知道說地震發生過會造成印利改變
But we don't know what its Indian state was in its original state
但是它原始的時候它的印利狀態是什麼我們不曉得
Because the recovery period of the earthquake is very long
因為地震的回復周期很長
So we say that we need to understand the process of an earthquake
那所以說我們對於要了解一個地震的過程
In fact, only from the past 100 years or the last 20 or 30 years
事實上光是從過去一百年或者是最近二三十年來關生
this is insufficient
這是源源不足
right
對
Okay, thank you
好謝謝
So it's still unknown
所以目前還是未知數
quite difficult for the present
對目前有相當大難度
right
對
Thanks
謝謝
well the lady is behind
好這位小姐在後面
i want to ask
我想請問一下
I was just curious
是我剛好奇
Just got the orange one that can measure pressure
剛有跟那個橘色可以測壓力的
The one you said can only be used once
你說只能用一次的那個
Then I want to ask how long it can last
那我想請問一下它可以用多久
In addition, on that land, measurement is prediction
那另外就是在那個陸地上在測量就是預測
It is the part to measure the possible slippage of the earthquake
就是測量可能那個地震的滑溢的部分
That's because the geology of each place is different
那因為每個地方它的地質不一樣
that includes it underground possibly
那包括它地下可能
there may be some that flow by themselves
可能有一些本身就會流動
For example, groundwater or some
譬如說地下水或是一些
It's like comparing minerals, fluid minerals, etc.
就是比較礦物之類的流體礦物之類
Will it be like this
那這樣子會不會在
Would it interfere with you measuring that
會不會干擾你在測量那個
just maybe it's slipping on the plate
就是可能它在板塊滑移
Or something related to earthquake prediction
或者是一些相關地震預測的部分
Thanks
謝謝
The instrument just mentioned
剛剛講的這個儀器
That one-time instrument is dependent on the battery
那個一次性的儀器就是取決於電池
how long the battery lasts
電池可以多久
if we have a good battery
如果我們有很好的電池
it can last five to ten years
它可以撐五到十年
right
對
But if, for example, the instrument
但是如果譬如說那個儀器
Sometimes there are problems because
有時候會有些問題是因為
when we set up
我們布設的時候
maybe some sea breakers
可能有些海底散崩
it sometimes buries that instrument
它有時候會把那個儀器埋起來
Then let's send the deep wave signal
那我們去傳遞深波訊號
when it's time to wake up to work
叫它起床工作的時候
maybe there is no way
可能就沒辦法就是
We will just because if it is buried after
我們會就是因為它如果被埋起來之後
it may be difficult
可能就很難
That instrument may not be useful
那個儀器可能就沒有用了
Because there are actually some
因為海底下事實上還是有一些
some subsea avalanches
一些海底的散崩
Then if we don't when it's time to deploy
然後如果我們不當是布設的時候
Maybe the position of the one-flag spin is not good enough
可能一旗旋的位置不夠好的話
there will be such a situation
會有這種狀況
Basically its life is related to the battery
基本上它的壽命是跟電池有關
If we can buy a good battery
如果說我們可以買一個好的電池的話
Basically it can last five to ten years
基本上它可以撐五到十年
Another question is that
另外一個問題就是說
If some of the signals we see are related to groundwater
如果說有些我們看到的訊號是跟地下水有關
Could it be related to the news-making of these environments?
會不會是跟這些環境的造訊有關
indeed it will
的確是會的
How do we distinguish
那我們怎麼樣去區分
That is to say, it is related to the environment
就是說它是跟環境有關
or we measured these terranes
還是我們量到這些地體的
Signals of activity on these faults
這些斷層活動的訊號
the first is to say
首先就是說
when we have this doubt
當我們有這個懷疑的時候
we will collect
我們就會去蒐集
That place, for example, water level data, gas tank data
那個地方譬如說水位資料氣箱資料
Then do the comparison
然後去做比對
and then go and take all of these neighbors
然後去把所有這些鄰近的所有的
The behavior of the test stations is used for comparison
測站的行為拿來一起做對比
look it is very
看它是很
Local refers to the local behavior or the behavior of a large area
local就局部的行為還是說大範圍的區域都是這樣的行為
Then we can clarify
那我們就可以去釐清就是說
this behavior is
這個行為是
more local or regional
比較局部的還是是區域性的
Then it may have something to do with the environment
然後它可能是不是跟環境是有關係的
But this requires dissection
但是這是需要抽屍波解
and you need to collect a lot of different data
而且需要蒐集很多不同的資料
That is indeed the data
那的確這個資料
If it were possible for observers on the surface to record these inquiries about these environments
要是地表這些觀察家是有可能紀錄到這些環境的這些造詢
Excuse me Dr. Xu
請問許博士
Which areas around Taipei are areas with fault zones?
台北周遭有哪些地區屬於有斷層帶的部位
Now, what kind of monitoring is the government doing?
然後以目前來講政府是有做一些什麼樣的監測
and some information to inform the public
以及有告知民眾的一些訊息
Thanks
謝謝
In fact, the main active fault in Taiwan
其實台灣的主要的活動斷層
In fact, the Geographical Information Survey Institute has declassified
地資調查所事實上都有去分類
It has different active faults and different levels
它有分不同的活動斷層還有分不同的等級
Then each has a different definition
然後各有不同的定義
Well, there are actually some monitors on these faults.
那這些斷層上面其實也有一些監測
There is regular monitoring data
就是有定期的監測資料
like some of these gps jean is
像有些這些GPS的詹就是
Why is his job continuous Zhan is to monitor
他的工作為什麼是連續詹就是要去監測
It is to continuously monitor the deformation of these surfaces.
就是持續的去監測這些地表的變形
But now the difficulty is to say that the fault precedes the activity
但是現在難處在於就是說斷層在活動之前
Everyone pays attention to the front move phenomenon on him.
他身上大家都很關注前招現象
But the former move is actually very concerned in the world at present
但前招其實目前在世界上也很關注
It is the observation of the frontlight phenomenon of earthquakes
就是地震的這個前照現象的觀測
In fact, there has been no major breakthrough
其實一直以來都沒有很大的突破
because of the considerable difficulty
因為有相當程度的困難
So while we monitor
所以雖然我們做監測
But we do monitor the data
但是我們做監測這些資料
it can tell you
它可以告訴你說
Areas of possible future rupture
將來可能發生的破裂的區域
probably somewhere
大概是什麼地方
But it is difficult for us to tell you exactly
但是我們很難精準的告訴大家
what time is it going to happen
是什麼時間要發生
it's more difficult
這是比較難的
there are three here
這邊有三位
this way first
這邊先來
Dr. Hsu, thank you for talking about this
許博士謝謝您講這些
let us know something
讓我們知道一些事情
I just want to ask
我想問一下就是說
can you add some
能不能幫我們補充一些
Which legends are more scientifically based?
有關哪些傳說是比較有科學依據的哪些
For example, the appearance of Emperor Yu represents the occurrence of an earthquake.
比如說皇帝於的出現代表地震的發生
Or biological changes
或者是說生物的異動
Or something that has no scientific basis
或者是哪些是沒有科學依據的
Let us in our ordinary life
讓我們在平常的生活當中
There is also some will to judge
也有一些判斷的意志
At noon they are for creatures when the earthquake comes
中午他們對於生物在地震來的時候
they did a lot of research
他們做了很多很多的研究
My own reaction to this creature actually
我本人其實對這個生物的反應
because if you want to include these as earthquake precursors
因為如果說你想要把這些納入當作是地震前兆
That's every time these animals have these reactions
那就是每次這些動物有這些反應的時候
you will have an earthquake
你都要有地震發生
right
對不對
If we only look at the earthquake precursors now, then we can say in hindsight
如果我們現在做地震前兆只是去看就事後諸葛說
Our cat didn't sleep before this earthquake or something
這個地震發生之前我們家那個貓就不睡覺或是怎樣
so it's kind of like
這樣就有點就是
It's because you're an afterthought
就是你有點事後的
If we really want to study precursors we have to be
如果我們真的想要研究前兆我們必須要就是
what is the normal behavior of this animal
這個動物平常的行為是什麼樣子
That is, he can correspond to an earthquake every time there is an abnormality
那是他就是每次異常的時候都可以對應到一個地震
But if this cannot be established
但是如果這個不能成立的時候
It's hard for you to convince others to say
你就很難去說服別人說
my creature
我的這個生物
This starts with some behaviors of some animals
這個先某些動物的一些行為
can be used to predict earthquakes
是可以用來預測地震的
right
對
so
所以
Some can, some can't, probably not
有些可以有些不可以大概不是
hundred percent
百分之百
right
對
it's hard to be sure
就很難完全確定
Because this is not the same as forecasting weather
因為這個跟預測氣象
Actually something is different
其實有些不太一樣
Because if the earthquake is predicted
因為預測地震的話
If you keep saying the earthquake is coming
如果你一直說地震要來
earthquake is coming
地震要來
You didn't even come
結果你都沒有來
The next time you say an earthquake is coming
你下次說地震要來的時候
everyone stop running
大家就不跑了
OK
OK
At this time, if an earthquake strikes
那這時候如果地震來的時候
it will be very serious
就會很慘重
So if your climate forecast is inaccurate
那如果說你氣候預測不準
That's actually
那其實
The consequences would be less severe
後果會比較不是那麼嚴重
Compared with earthquake prediction
跟地震預測比起來
So earthquake prediction actually has
所以地震預測其實還有
quite a long way to go
相當長的一條路是要走的
ok get ready
好 準備信聲
hello please ask
你好 請教一下
that volcano erupted
那個火山爆發
Will it drive that fault zone to rupture?
會不會帶動那個斷層帶破裂
Is there a causal relationship between them?
他們之間有沒有那個因果關係
like that
譬如說像那個
Kameyama is old and quite close to the Ryukyu Trench
龜山老舊蠻接近那個琉球海溝
For example, the Tatun Volcanic Society
那譬如說像那個大屯火山會
next to it is the one
它旁邊就是那個
Mountain Foot Fault
山脂腳斷層
Is there any kind of
那這兩者有沒有那種
cause and effect thank you
因果關係 謝謝
it is indeed possible
這的確是有可能的
because like
因為像
2016 Yumoto Earthquake, Japan
2016年日本雄本地震
it is it yumoto earthquake
它是它雄本地震
that earthquake
那個地震
It actually happened on the south side of Aso Volcano
事實上是在阿蘇火山的南邊發生
But after that earthquake
但是在那個地震發生過後
Volcanoes have some relatively violent activities
火山就有一些比較劇烈的活動
On the contrary
反之的話
Because you just have some movement of these earthquakes or volcanoes
因為你只要有這些地震或火山的一些運動
It will cause changes in Indonesia in that area
它就會造成那個區域印尼的改變
That does have the potential to trigger activity on nearby faults.
那的確是有可能會引發附近斷層的活動
there is this possibility
是有這個可能性的
the student
這位學生
The student I want to consult is my first department
我想要請教就是我第科系的學生
Then I noticed that some instruments introduced just now are
那我有注意到剛剛有介紹一些儀器是
put it over there
放置在那邊
and maybe a year later
然後可能過一年之後再去
Look at the data it collects
看它採集到的數據
what i want to ask is
那我想要問的是
Earthquake early warning systems are now available at
現在有地震的預警系統可以在
after the earthquake has occurred
地震已經發生之後
Send alerts to people's mobile phones
趕快送警報到民眾的手機
Then I want to ask if there is any instrument
那我想要問有沒有儀器是
continuous monitoring
持續監測
Then minutes before a possible earthquake,
然後在可能地震快要發生前幾分鐘
forecast
就可以提出預報了
this may be difficult
這個可能有困難
just with everyone
就跟大家
I just told you the same
剛剛我跟大家講一樣
that is
就是說
Because what kind of so-called precursor phenomenon will occur before the earthquake
因為現在地震之前會有什麼樣的所謂的前兆現象
Because we don't see many such cases now
因為我們現在並沒有看到很多有這樣的case
Presumably there are successful predictions in the literature
大概文獻上有成功的被預報
That is, there was a successful early warning before the earthquake.
就是地震前有成功預警
Actually Haicheng Earthquake
實際上是海城地震
It should be that the Haicheng earthquake in 1976 was successful
應該是1976年海城地震是有成功
All other earthquakes are not recognized by scientists
其他所有的地震都是不被科學家承認的
was successful
是有成功的
so honestly
所以老實說
What to do before an earthquake
地震前會有什麼樣的行為
Actually we don't know
其實我們是不曉得的
Again because of this relationship
又是因為這個關係
So it is difficult for you to say that before the earthquake
所以你也很難說地震發生前
Hurry up and tell everyone that an earthquake is about to happen
趕快告訴大家是地震要發生
Actually it's quite difficult
其實這是蠻困難的
Earthquake warning means
地震預警的就是說
If your earthquake is far away from you
如果你地震離你很遠
that it happened now
那它現在發生了
Because it takes a while for the wave to reach you
因為波傳到你這邊需要一段時間
so if you get farther away from you
所以你如果離你越遠
You'll have more time to make early warnings
你就有比較多時間可以去做預警
like a tsunami
就像海嘯
Because the tsunami propagation speed may be hundreds of kilometers per hour
因為海嘯傳播速度可能是每小時幾百公里
So if you compare earthquakes that occur farther away
所以如果你比較發生在比較遠的地震
you know it happened
你知道它發生了
That's because the wave spread to Taiwan may be
那因為波傳到台灣可能是
It takes a while, then you may have tens of seconds and minutes
需要段時間 那你就可能有幾十秒幾分鐘
or have an hour left to do these preparations
或是剩一小時的時間可以做這些準備
But what if it happened near Taiwan?
但是如果呢 就發生在台灣附近的話
In fact, because it waves the boat because the distance is very close
那事實上 因為它波船 因為距離很近
So you soon this burrow will come
所以你很快 這個地洞就來
You might be too late to run, right?
你可能跑都來不及了 對
It was just said that one was admitted to predict success
那剛有說有一個被承認是預測成功
Then why was that scene predictable?
那為什麼那一場可以預測到呢
because its symptoms are obvious, yes
因為它的徵兆很明顯 對
What are the signs?
是有哪些徵兆呢
it was just before the earthquake
它就是在地震發生之前
it has some noticeable deformation
它有一些明顯的地的變形
Crustal deformation, they did some leveling
地殼變形 它們有做一些水準測量
For vertical traces of two layers of earth
就兩層地表的垂直微量
it found some obvious changes
它發現有一些很明顯的改變
And before the earthquake
然後在地震發生之前呢
it has foreshocks it has dense foreshocks
它有前震 有密集的前震
There are dense earthquakes, small earthquakes, yes
有密集的一些地震發生 小地震發生 對
Then this is the beginning, the warning
然後這時候就是開始就是預警
Yes please evacuate
對 請大家疏散
That earthquake was a success, yes
那個地震是有成功 對
But the long mountain in the back is right behind
但是後面的那個長山就緊接在後面
Also nearby. That one didn't work out.
也是在附近 那個就沒有成功
right
對
so
所以
Controversy is still quite big
爭議還是蠻大的
ok sir
好 這位先生
I want to ask Dr. Xu about the recent neutral blog
我想要請教許博士 最近那個中立博
Neutral betting is gravitational betting
中立博就是引力博
get the nobel prize
得到諾貝爾獎
I've seen this before
那我也曾經看過說這個
Earth's electric plane may be
地球的電力層 可能對
predict
預測
like this last generation
像這個以末代的
this possibility
這個可能性
Does Professor Xu have any information on this?
許教授有沒有任何這方面的訊息
About our power layer
關於這個我們的電力層
The onboard power layer is predictable
搭載的電力層可以預測
our earthquake
我們的地震
Well, yesterday I saw a message saying
那麼昨天我看到一個消息說
This golden heel on earth
地球上的這個金跟
radiation of copper
銅的輻射性
when the volcano erupts
就是火山爆發的時候
Might be able to see that radiation beneath us
可能可以看到我們地層底下那個輻射
that radiation
那個輻射線
that creates the geographic layer
那就造成地理層
electric wire
電線
The atmosphere, the electrotransfer layer, should have followed the atmosphere
大氣層,電移層,應該是還大氣層跟上去了
These changes are important for us to predict earthquakes
這些的變動對於我們預測地震
Is there any current scientific evidence
有沒有任何目前科學上的證據
For the electrotransfer layer
對於電移層
An old hole created by an earthquake in the electrotransfer layer
地震在電移層上造成的老洞
Indeed, some can be observed online
的確是有些線上可以被觀測到的
But just like I said earlier
但是就跟我剛剛前面講
In fact such an old hole line like this
事實上這樣的老洞線這樣
It happens even when there are no earthquakes
在平常沒有地震的時候它也會發生
becomes saying that if we really want to use this
變成說如果我們真的想要用這個
Help come and go to understand the pre-creation of earthquakes
幫忙來去了解地震的前造化
we have to explain
我們就必須解釋說
What kind of abnormal phenomena
到底哪些這樣的異常現象
Could all these anomalies lead to an earthquake?
是不是所有這些異常現象都會帶一個地震出來
but if there is no
但是如果是沒有的話
how high is your accuracy
那你的準確率有多高
For example because if you are generally right or wrong
譬如說因為如果你一般對錯
just a normal chance
就是一般一般的機會
So I think your accuracy
所以我覺得你的準確率
at least seventy percent
至少是百分之七十以上
It can be said that it is more feasible
才能算說比較有可行
Because you guessed it was normal
因為你猜有跟沒有是一般一般
That's at least what you're going to do if you're going to use this method
那至少就是你如果要用這個方法
Regardless of the method, when you learn about earthquake prediction
不管是任何方法 你去了解預測地震的時候
So can you reach this threshold?
那你是不是可以達到這個門檻
It's not that everyone is talking about it after the earthquake
而不是說地震發生後之後大家才在說
i see this which i see
我看到這個 我看到哪個
This becomes less scientifically based.
這個就變成比較沒有科學上的依據這樣子
ok here's another question
好 這邊還有一位問題
Ask Dr. Xu
請教一下許博士
Because I do avoidable things with my kids
因為我跟我的孩子做可避的
We must be very interested in observing the natural environment
我們對自然環境的觀察一定有非常有興趣
A few years ago we went to the Zhenyang point of Jiufen 23
幾年前我們去過九分二三的鎮陽點
Want to see a lot of wet damage protruding from the ground
想看到地上突出了很多濕損
We don't quite understand what kind of power this is
我們不太了解這是什麼樣的力量
what kind of action
什麼樣的作用方式
where does its history come from
它的歷史來自哪個方面
would stick out the surface so much moisture damage
會把地表突出了這麼多的濕損
Can Dr. Hsu tell us, please?
可以請許博士告訴我們一下嗎
Wet damage Because of wet damage, it is usually when you are at noon
濕損 因為濕損的話一般是你在中午時
And because of that low relationship
然後因為那個低的關係
It is the action of the water flow that creates
就是那個水流的作用才會生成了
The death loss was how it was lifted up from the ground before
那個死損是以前在地下被抬上來是怎樣
Because as far as I know there shouldn't be
因為據我所知那邊應該沒有
Limestone
就是石灰岩
So there should be no casualties.
所以應該是不會有死損才對
That might not necessarily be a death loss
那有可能不見得一定是死損
For example, if you eat lightly
譬如說你差異輕食
For example, if you say rock
譬如說你岩石的話
If your rock composition has strong and weak
如果你岩石組成有強跟弱
That's because if it's exposed to the surface
那因為如果它暴露到地表上的話
because of your rain
因為你雨水的作用
it washes out some of the weaker rocks first
它會把一些比較弱的岩石先清洗掉
the harder stuff stays there
那比較硬的東西就會留在那裡
Then maybe it will produce a shape like this
那也許就會產生那樣的一個形狀這樣子
ok wait a minute
好 等一下
Is there anything else here?
還有沒有其他的這邊
the lady
這位女士
Have been to the Taichung Science and Technology Museum
有到那個台中科博館
they have an address delay
他們有一個地址延遲
That's because of the plate movement we've seen before
那因為以前我們看到的板塊運動
It's all because of Zhang Lie at the central level
都是說因為中央級張烈
then push the plate
然後推動板塊
make plates collide
使得板塊碰撞
Then the ocean can be silent
然後海洋地可隱默
But its new saying is that
可是它的那個新說法是說
Because the plate on the edge of the plate is older
因為板塊的邊緣的那個板塊年紀比較大
so it cools
所以它冷卻了
It becomes denser after cooling
冷卻了以後密度比較大
so it's silent
所以它就隱默
and because of its obscurity
然後因為它的隱默
Only then did he pull Zhang Lie at the central level behind him
才拉扯後面的中央級張烈
Then my new way of speaking
那我對於這種新的講法
because i haven't heard of it before
因為我以前沒有聽說過
In that exercise, it was talking about this
那一次演習它就是針對這個在講
so i don't know what the doctor said about this
所以我不知道博士對於這一種說法
move with the old plate
跟舊的板塊運動
It was promoted by Zhang Lie at the central level
是因為中央級張烈而推動
plate collision
板塊碰撞
Then keep quiet about which one would make more sense.
然後隱默到底哪一個會比較有道理
No both exist
沒有 這兩個都是存在的
Because the tiles are generated when the Central Group
因為板塊在中央集團生成的時候
It just pushes the oceanic plate to the side
它就是把海洋板塊往兩邊推
Then the final process is due to the relationship of gravity
然後以末的過程因為重力的關係
It actually brings the plates down
它事實上把板塊是往下帶
So both forces work
所以這兩種作用力都有作用
both work
都有作用
It's just that the place of action is different
只是說作用的地點不一樣
But it's all driven by plate movement
但是都是板塊運動一個驅使的動力
both have always been
兩個都是 一直以來都是
because it was emphatically saying
因為它當時強調是說
In fact, it is not the central set that pushes the plates to collide
其實並不是中央集推動板塊去碰撞
It's that the central set was pulled apart after the plates disappeared.
而是板塊隱沒了以後把中央集拉開的
It has been emphasized that the point is
它一直強調這一點是
Concealing first and centering pulling out later
隱沒在先而中央集拉開在後
I'm not sure which of these two forces contributes more
這兩個力誰的貢獻比較大我不確定
But at least all I knew was
但是至少我以前知道的就是
Both forces are plate action
這兩個力都是板塊作用
It is the driving force provided by the plate movement
就是板塊運動裡面提供的驅動力
I remember Zhang Lie very much
想起的張烈很
that is
就是說
The implicit contribution is also
隱默的貢獻也
that's right
也有就對了
it's you
就是你
when the earth culverts upwards
地涵往上擁的時候
he will put
他會把
Both active and passive
主動跟被動都有
right
對
then when silent
然後隱默的時候
because of gravity
因為重力的關係
he would have been down
他本來就會下層
so he'll pull it down
所以他會把它往下拉
So these two effects
所以這兩個作用
should have both
應該都有才對
OK thank you
OK 謝謝
ok there's one behind
好 有一位在後面
Hello Dr. Xu
許博士你好
I'm a postdoc at that autobiographical center
我是那個自傳中心的博士後
He wants to consult with Dr.
他想跟博士請教一下
just say
就說
like the one just now
像剛剛那個
the one under the ground
地底下的那個
Sensing instrument
感測儀器
is that possible
那是不是可以
like tie a rope
比方說綁個繩子
Then
然後
wait till it's decided
等到沒定就把它
pull it up like this
拉起來這樣
reuse
重複使用
I have no idea
我不知道
And then there is that
然後還有就是說
just saw it
剛好看到就是
under the sea
在海底
just dive
就是潛下去
dive down
潛下去
to measure
去量測
His lower status
他下層的那個狀況
in this way
這樣子
will that be that
那會不會那個
In case of the influence of that tide
萬一有那個潮汐的影響
would be less accurate like this
會比較不準確這樣
Still flat
還平面的
Rise and fall
上升下降
The last one is to say
那最後一個就是說
Just now the doctor announced the dynamic changes of the tsunami
剛剛那博士有放海嘯動態的變化
Will there be a typhoon at that time?
會不會當時有發生颱風的話
Will it have some influence on him?
會不會對他有一些影響
For example, it may increase the speed of the wave boat or something.
比如說可能加快了海浪船的速度之類的
Thanks
謝謝
ok i try to remember all your questions
好 我試著記得你所有的問題
Can the first one be tied with a rope?
第一個是不是可以綁過一條繩子
of course not
當然是不行
because i think you should be
因為我覺得你應該是
Actually, I don't know if you have ever engaged in marine activities.
其實我不知道你有沒有從事海上活動
Because our instruments are at least ten or twenty kilograms
因為我們的儀器至少是十二十公斤
Then you put in the water to a depth of 2,000 meters
然後你放水深是兩千米
basically you can't
基本上你是不可能
Because that resistance is too great
因為那個阻力太大了
In fact, as long as you are about tens of meters, you are fine.
其實你只要大概可能幾十米還可以
One or two hundred meters is OK
一兩百米還OK
But 4,000 meters is very difficult
但是四千米難度就非常高
so it is impossible to tie the rope
所以是不可能綁繩子
We're now actually going to have an aluminum ground setup
我們現在事實上就是會有一個鋁地的裝置
That means after we sink the instrument to the bottom of the ocean now
就是說我們現在把儀器沉到海底之後
Then let's say we turn off the car
然後譬如說我們關車
Then when the time comes we'll hand it over
然後時間到我們會把它交行
Then it will have a
然後它會有一個
Ruins' device
Ruins的裝置
so it will float up
所以它就會浮上來
And then it will flash when it comes up
然後浮上來之後它會閃光
then we can
那我們就可以
find where this instrument is
去找找這個儀器在哪裡
But our instruments are sometimes taken away by Yunming
但是我們的儀器有時候會被雲鳴撈走
Then blackmail us like this
然後在勒索我們這樣子
Hehehe
呵呵呵
right then
對 然後
next thing you said
接下來你講的是
Well
呃
Will it be affected by tides?
會不會受潮汐影響
The tide is changing because of the tide
那潮汐因為潮汐的變動
it is cycle
它是週期
it is recoverable
它是可恢復的
That
那
This deformation of the earth is irreversible
地的這個變形它是不可恢復的
So it is easy to distinguish
所以這是很容易區分
and the tidal cycle
而且潮汐的週期
The main cycle is 12 hours
主要的週期是12個小時
Well
呃
just uh
就是呃
12 hours 20 hours
12個小時 20小時
Its several Modes are
它幾個Mode都是
do you know how often it is
你知道它頻率是多少
So basically you're not going to talk to the normal
所以基本上你是不會跟一般的這些
Earthquake or plate movement signal
地震或是板塊運動訊號
is mixed together
是混在一起
because of the tide
因為潮汐
Our human study of tides
我們人類對潮汐的研究
Scientists have thoroughly studied tides
科學家對潮汐的研究其實是滿透徹的
It's all these Mode it
它所有的這些Mode它
it has
它都有
how much each frequency
每一個頻率是多少
have very detailed records
都有很詳細的記錄
then you say
然後你說
when the typhoon comes
颱風來的時候
if there is a tsunami
如果有海嘯
Will the typhoon affect the tsunami?
颱風會不會影響海嘯
Then I want to answer yes
然後我要回答是
Tsunamis are very different from typhoons
海嘯跟颱風很不一樣
because of the tsunami
因為海嘯的話
It's because of the sea worm's misalignment
它是因為海蟲發生錯動
so you whole sea worm
所以你整個海蟲
The one where all of the above seawater happens
以上的所有的海水都發生的一個
are affected by fluctuations
就是都會受到波動影響
But the general sea breeze
但是一般海風的話
It's just that the sea water is very submerged.
就是海水的很潛沉
you will be affected
你會受到影響
but you won't affect deep
但是你不會影響到很深的地方
So your typhoon is actually a comparative
所以你颱風事實上就是比較
surface movement
表層的運動
But the tsunami is a deep movement
但是海嘯它就是一個深的運動
So why can it spread so
所以它為什麼可以傳播這麼
it can actually span the entire pacific
它事實上可以跨過整個太平洋
For example, an earthquake reaching the sea of ​​South America
傳到比如說南美洲的海的地震
its tsunami could travel to japan
它的海嘯可以傳播到日本
Is it because it is a holistic movement
它是不是因為它是一個整體性的運動
Then because your sea worm is comparing the ocean
然後因為你的海蟲在比較大洋
Because the water is deeper
因為海水面比較深
When it reaches the land, its sea water
那到了陸地它的海水
that sea worm will become shallow
那個海蟲就會變淺
So the wave height of your tsunami will become higher
那所以你海嘯的那個波高就會變高
like a water gun
就像一個水槍一樣
will cause great harm
會產生很大的危害
So the typhoon should not affect
所以颱風應該是不會影響
Trump's Slave
川普的奴隙
good
好
ok if there is no question i would like to ask a question
好 如果沒有問題 我想問一個問題
you just saw taiwan
你剛剛看到臺灣
our island
我們島上
Lots and lots of that GPS
很多很多那個GPS的
How many stations are there?
站 大概有多少個
Now there are more than 400
現在有400多個
400 means all of you all
400 就是說全部大家全部
different units
不同單位
More than 400 units put up
各個單位放上去的400多個
Then what we have is longer
那我們有的是比較久一點
put it long ago
很久以前放的
Some are relatively new
有的是比較新的放的
then we know that now
那我們知道說現在
These instruments are more and more advanced
這些儀器越來越進步
because everyone's mobile phone
因為每個人的手機上面
the GPS one
GPS的那個
The sensitivity is getting higher and higher
靈敏度也就越來越高了
Then
然後
because of your measurement
因為你的量測
you don't need to know every second
你不需要知道每一秒
You measure it about once a day
你大概一天去量一次
calibration primary
校正一次
take one
取一個
data is enough
data也就夠了
Then our current chip
然後我們現在的晶片
that more and more
那個越來越
It may be getting smaller and smaller
可能是越來越做越小
Power consumption is getting less and less
耗電也越來越少
Then it can be released indefinitely sometimes
然後它有的時候還可以無限放出來
Needless to say, people have to peel the grass
就不必說人去把那個要把草剝開
go find that thing
去找那個東西
we can know around there
我們可以知道在那附近
Then use the side of your instrument to put that
然後用你的儀器一側就把那個
All the signals are passed on
所有的信號就傳遞過來了
The things in its memory can be passed here.
它記憶裡面的東西就可以傳到這邊來了
Are you going this way now?
現在是不是有在往這方面走
It's very convenient if you go this way
如果往這方面走就很方便
unnecessary
不必要
We don't need hard-working students
我們不必要大概很辛苦的學生
Go to every deep mountain to dig up the grass
到每一個深山去把草挖開
You can be within a few meters of that
你可以就在那個附近幾公尺內
You can catch that signal
你就可以把那個信號給抓到了
Or let it go to the base station to go to the whole
或者讓它去傳送到基地台去整個
That is to say, we can digitize it as soon as possible.
就是說一可以就把它電子化
Then this we can go to
然後這個我們可以去
This data will be more convenient to obtain
這個data會取得比較方便一點
Because in fact because of the mountains
因為其實因為山區
Mountains are the worst place for communications
山區是通訊最不好的地方
Because Chunghwa Telecom is a place where people live
因為中華電信就是有人居住的地方
good communication quality
通訊品質很好
The situation in the mountains where no one lives is actually very bad
沒人居住的地方山區的情況其實是很不好
so
所以說
Maybe in cities or major cities
也許在城市或是主要一些城市
Your cell phone coverage is actually pretty good
你手機訊號的覆蓋率其實很好
But after going to the mountains, there are actually big problems
但是到山區之後其實有很大的問題
In fact, we encountered a big problem in the transmission in the mountainous area
其實我們在山區的傳輸碰到很大的問題
Even if we have recorded
就算是我們有記錄到
But the signal can't come out, people still have to go there
但是訊號傳不出來人還是得要過去
this is a problem
這是一個問題
In addition to that
另外就是說
Because we do confidential positioning
因為我們做的是機密的定位
then we have to know
然後我們必須要知道
We have to have some control points on the surface
我們在地表上必須要有些控制點
That point cannot be moved
那個點是不能移動的
because what we need to know is to say
因為我們需要知道就是說
Its change over time today
它的隨時今天變化量
So if our mobile phone can be used as a Receiver
所以說如果說我們手機可以當作Receiver的話
Become means its position every time
變成就是說它每次擺放的位置
is to be in a fixed position
就是都要在固定的位置
still have to fix
還是要固定
just its electron
只是它的電子
Its components will get smaller and smaller
它的元件會越來越小
Could it be that this instrument will get better and better?
會不會是這個儀器會越做越好
Of course, the instruments are getting smaller and smaller
儀器當然是就是越做越小
It will be more convenient for us to do field work
就我們做野外工作會比較方便
but that is to say
但是就是說
If we want to make good progress on positioning
如果我們希望到定位進度好
very precise
很精準的話
then we wish to say
那我們就希望說
where everything is placed
一切都是擺在哪裡
That point is not moving
就是那個點是不動的
But if I measure today
但是如果我今天去測量
I may be a little crooked
我稍微可能歪了一下
or if it is not quite right
或者是沒有對得很準的話
Maybe my coordinates are not so precise
也許我的坐標就不是那麼精準
That's because of the map and deformation we're looking at
那因為我們看的這個地圖和變形
is very tiny
是很微小的
That kind of error is actually very difficult
那這樣的誤差其實很難
just not allowed
就是不被允許的
right
對
so i see your picture
所以我看你那個照片
You want three corners to stand over there
你要三個角要立在那邊
very fixed
很固定
It must be very stable to put something on it
上面架一個東西要很穩定
Yes, just keep calm
對 就是要定心定平
and we have that
而且我們對那個
to that spherical position
對到那個球性的位置
Then the height should be measured accurately
然後高度也要量得很準
And it takes a long time
而且要量很久
because from
因為從
Actually that's it
其實就是這樣
Because your car generally uses these positioning
因為你汽車一般用的這些定位
Maybe a few meters error
可能是幾米的誤差
but we sat
但是我們坐的是
Kilometer error
公里的誤差
So that level is much different
所以那個等級差很多
So we rely on
所以我們要靠就是
Good instrument and long-term implementation
好的儀器跟長時間的貫徹
Then there is a way to achieve
然後才有辦法去達到
The progress of this positioning of the minimeter
那個minimeter的這個定位的進度
right
對
It should be possible in the future
將來應該是可以
Because we actually have some
因為我們其實現在有一些
cheaper receiver
比較便宜的receiver
that is
就是
become smaller and smaller
就變得越來越小
But it's small words that become words
但是它就是小的話變成就是說
You want to spread a large area
你要布很大的範圍
That is, the distance between your sides should be shortened.
就是你的側佔的間距要變短
Then the observation time will be longer
然後觀測時間要變長
Density is going to be higher
密度要變高
So it's hatchback to balance
所以這是兩廂要平衡
right
對
And I just said that we are laying things on the bottom of the sea
還有剛剛說在海底上布東西
And because it goes through a lot of sea water on it
然後因為它經過上面有很多海水
So it transmits this GPS signal
所以它傳遞這個GPS的信號
can't get out of this sea
出不了這個海水
so you're going to use deep wave on the side
所以你要在旁邊用深波
to talk to it to test it
去跟它做交流去測它
Why is this measurement
為什麼這個測量要
because you are near the United States
因為你到美在附近
You just have a few boards down there
你只是只有幾個板在下面而已
It takes 24 hours to pick up this signal
需要24小時去接這個信號
Because in seawater it actually
因為海水裡面它其實
Because the sea itself is always moving
因為海水它本身它一直在動
So its own
所以說它本身的
It's the deep wave transmission
就是那個深波傳遞上
When it comes up, it is that the change of deep wave speed will be quite large.
上來的時候 它的就是 深波速度的變化其實會蠻大
Because it is different from yours, such as the temperature of sea water, there will be some changes
因為它跟你的 譬如海水的溫度會有一些變化
And then the walrus changes, and these are the sources of the so-called errors
然後海象會變化 這些都是所謂的誤差的來源
Let's just say, what if we can collect as many observations as possible?
隨便說 如果說呢 我們能盡可能的收集多的觀測資料
We can try to eliminate these errors as much as possible.
我們就可以盡量去把這些誤差去消除掉
Because it's inside because there are a lot of internal waves in the sea
因為它裡面 因為海水有很多是內波什麼
These things are difficult for you to eliminate with models
這些東西都是你很難用模型去消除的
The only way is if you observe long enough
唯有的方法就是你觀測時間夠長
And then because the path between your two deep waves to that ship is similar
然後呢 因為你兩個深波到那個船上那個路徑是類似的
Then you can use the differential method to slightly eliminate these signals
那你可以用差分法把這些 這些訊號稍微消除一些
But if you want to achieve good observation progress
但是如果要達到很好的觀測進度
Or the more observations, the better
還是觀測量是越多越好
Or you use two boats and put that cost cost
或者你用兩條船 把那個成本 成本
This is a matter of cost and popularity
這是成本的問題 還有人緣的問題
Yes because we do now, do this sea word
對 因為我們現在做 做這個海上的話
Basically, the wind and waves are sometimes very strong
基本上風浪有時候很大
Many people have at least half
很多人至少有一半以上
probably not working at sea
可能是不是的在海上作業的
Yes, because we do this
對 就是因為我們做這個是
you have work to do at sea
你在海上是要做事的
so you have to keep
所以你必須要保持
is working
是可以工作的狀態
no cloud boat
不能夠有雲船
first request
第一個要求
ok, is there anything else
好 那其他還有沒有什麼
Questions everyone wants to ask
大家想要問的問題
Then I think everyone understands
那我想大家是不是都很了解了
not too many problems
沒有太多的問題
if so
那如果這樣的話
we're ending the day a little early
我們今天就稍微提前結束
Thank you Dr. Xu again
那再次謝謝許博士
thank you all
謝謝大家
our this
我們這個
great speech
精彩的演講
I'm here to make a notice
那我這邊要做一個預告
we next month
我們下個月
Feast of Knowledge in November
11月的知識饗宴
it was on november 28
是在11月28號
We will go to the National Taiwan University campus
我們是會到台大院區的
Lecture Hall of the Institute of Atomic and Molecular Sciences
原子與分子科學研究所的演講廳
we will change the subject again
我們會再換一個題目
It's Xu Lifen, a researcher from the life science side.
是從生命科學那邊的徐立芬研究員
in the Agricultural Biotechnology Research Center of our hospital
是在本院農業生物科技研究中心
He will talk about when tradition meets modernity
他會主講是當傳統與現代相遇
We are going to discuss the effects of Taiwanese herbal medicine research on cancer
我們要討論台灣草藥研究癌症的效應
so welcome
所以歡迎大家
Information about this talk should be available on our website
應該可以在我們的網站上看到這個演講的訊息
Thank you again for coming to our feast of knowledge
再次謝謝大家來參加我們的知識饗宴
Good night
晚安